<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pleasaunt playne and pythye pathewaye leadynge to a vertues and honest lyfe no lesse profytable, then delectable. V.L.</title>
            <author>Leigh, Valentine, fl. 1562.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1522</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04975</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15113.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121899</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857058</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857058</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22727</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04975)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22727)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 134:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pleasaunt playne and pythye pathewaye leadynge to a vertues and honest lyfe no lesse profytable, then delectable. V.L.</title>
                  <author>Leigh, Valentine, fl. 1562.</author>
                  <author>Lynyng, Urban, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Nicolas Hyll, for Iohn Case, dwellynge at the sygne of the Baule, in Paules churche yarde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1552?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>V.L. = Valentine Leigh, whose first name appears in an anagram "Nitnelaue" on A2r line 14.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Urban Lynyng.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi²  A-E⁴ F² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A pleasaunte pathewaye leadynge to an honest lyfe.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 15421 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22727:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22727:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The pleaſaunt playne and <hi>py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye Pathewaye leadynge</hi> to a vertues and honeſt lyfe, no leſſe profytable, then delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>V. L.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprynted at London by Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Hyll, for Iohn Caſe, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge at the ſygne of the Baule, in Paules chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che yarde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:22727:2"/>
            <lg>
               <l>YE that in you the deſyre to knowe</l>
               <l>I good ware for to take,</l>
               <l>Wherby to ryches ye myght growe,</l>
               <l>And ydlenes to forſake,</l>
               <l>This lytle boke wyth dylygence</l>
               <l>Se that ye reade and marke,</l>
               <l>Throughly notynge the good ſence</l>
               <l>Contayned in this warke,</l>
               <l>Py thy precepts you ſhall here fynde,</l>
               <l>Ryghte pleaſaunte for to reade,</l>
               <l>Whereof perchaunce ſome youth are blynde,</l>
               <l>And thereof ſhall haue nede,</l>
               <l>Do not therefore deſpyſe this boke</l>
               <l>Becauſe it goeth in ryme,</l>
               <l>For they that on this boke doth loke,</l>
               <l>Shall fynde the matter fyne.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:22727:2"/>
            <head>The preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eynge gyftes are not ſo muche to be valued for the price of them as they are to be eſtemed for the good entente of the geuer (mooſte gentyll reader) my ſmall labours and trauayle herein beſtowed (whyche I frelye geue thee) I ſhal hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye deſyre thee to take in good parte, wherein althoughe the mattier be not in euerye poynte ſo exquiſytely handeled as my good wyll and ſeale coulde haue wyſhed it, yet I do nothynge at all myſtruſte but that ye wyll wyth fauoure beare wyth me, and rather frendlye wyncke at the faultes yf there be anye, then ſpytefullye as carpers at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mennes doynges ſeke occaſyon to dyſprayſe the ſame, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuche as the hole effecte thereof treateth of nothynge but of good and holſome counſayles enterlaced wyth pleaſaunt mirthe and honeſty, to youth no leſſe right profytable then neceſſarye. Licurgus, who for hys grauytie and excellente wyſedome gaue lawes vnto the Lacedimonians, amongeſt hys other laudable and ſeruyouſe ſtatutes, dyd inſtitute and ordayne a certayne kynde of exercyſe, at the whyche the elders whyche had borne rule in the common wealth, dyd commonly mete there, to paſſe the tyme wyth pleaſaunte talke and wyttye tales, but ſuche as were alwayes eyther profytable to the commendation and prayſe of honeſtye, or els to the deteſtynge and rebukynge of vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, becauſe he perfectlye well conſydered that it was a thynge mooſte nedefull and requyſet ſometyme wyth ſuche goodlye recreation to refreſhe the weakenyd powers of the mynde, that it myghte be thereby the more freſhe and apte to compaſſe and accomplyſhe other more wayghtye affayres. I omytte other probable auctorities whyche I myghte nowe worthelye brynge herein, to declare that thys lytle woorke is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected althoughe after a nomber of pythye preceptes there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth a merye inuented mattier placed therein onely to quyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſpyrytes and to aucyde tedyouſneſſe. And who is ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunte, but that he well vnderſtandeth that youthe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlye taketh more delectation in redynge thoſe thynges which in hys age requyreth then in graue ſentences cereouſlye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced. Yet here ſhall he learne yf he rede it wyth dylygence bothe howe to leade a quyet and godly lyfe in the feare of God, and alſo to exchue the aſſaultes of ſynne and daungers of the
<pb facs="tcp:22727:3"/>worlde, vnto this bryttell age, (I ſaye) therefore I haue wrytten this, and not the prudente well ſtryken in yeres, whoſe experience perchaunce hath ſufficiently taught, and who haue alredye paſſed the daungerouſe rockes, and ſwallowynge quicke ſandes of this troubleſome worlde. My honeſt meanynge therefore gentyll reader, herin, yf thou thanckfullye receyue, I ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be the more wyllynge to take ſome paynes in other mattiers. And ſo I wiſhe thee wel to fare.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:22727:3"/>
            <head>A pleaſaunte Pathewaye</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T chaunced that on the eleuenth daye.</l>
                  <l>Of the floryſhynge Moneth, of luſtye Maye,</l>
                  <l>When Titan, into Taurus, hys enterye began,</l>
                  <l>And the younge bloude, of euery creature than,</l>
                  <l>Renued hys ſtrength, and powers dyd reuiue.</l>
                  <l>So that eche thynge nowe, appeared on lyue,</l>
                  <l>Whiche in the ſtormye wynter, before,</l>
                  <l>Had ſuſtayned, Eolus Iſy blaſtes ſore,</l>
                  <l>And that the waterye Snowes, had them ſo torne,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, of the vehement rage, of Capricorne.</l>
                  <l>Whiche colde cloudye myſtes, once paſte theyr waye,</l>
                  <l>Eche thynge, receaued agayne corage, in hys araye,</l>
                  <l>And becauſe the ſharpe colde, hys malyce had done,</l>
                  <l>The Mauis endeuoured her ſelfe, fyrſt, her notes to tune.</l>
                  <l>Next after, the pleaſaunt Nightingale, tempered her voyce,</l>
                  <l>Which w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> her mery melody, euery heart, doth greatly reioyce,</l>
                  <l>The Thruſhe, the Blackebyrde, and the Grenefinche alſo.</l>
                  <l>In thys merye ſprynge tyme, dyd ſhe we what they coulde do,</l>
                  <l>And then alſo, the Sunne ſhynynge verye hote,</l>
                  <l>Cauſed the crabbed Cockowe, to declare her olde note,</l>
                  <l>In thys freſhe tyme, (I ſaye) for my recreation,</l>
                  <l>Into the woodes I walked, to take delectation,</l>
                  <l>Aſwell for to heare, the ioyfull byrdes ſynge,</l>
                  <l>As alſo to beholde, howe euerye thynge dyd ſprynge,</l>
                  <l>And ſhewe them ſelues, agayne, alyue in theyr kynde,</l>
                  <l>That in the wynter, were bare, and naked, to the rinde</l>
                  <l>Eche tre budded, and hys leaues gan to ſprede,</l>
                  <l>Eche herbe had hys floures, in euerye grene mede,</l>
                  <l>The Primeroſe, the Violet, were then in their prime,</l>
                  <l>And the ſwete ſmellynge courſloppe, floriſhed at thys tyme,</l>
                  <l>The Hauthorne, the Cheritre, and the Damaſcigne,</l>
                  <l>And eche Aple tre blomed, declarynge good ſigne,</l>
                  <l>That yf God their ſwete bloſſomines, wolde voucheſafe to ſaue,</l>
                  <l>Great ſtore of fruite, of them we ſhoulde haue,</l>
                  <l>And thus goynge alone, vnder the woode ſyde.</l>
                  <l>A fayre aged man, I ſhortelye eſpyde,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:4"/>
                  <l>And euen ſtrayght after me, he came a ſofte pace,</l>
                  <l>I ſtayed a lytle therwith, thynckinge in this care,</l>
                  <l>Thys olde man ſemeth, a man of grauitie,</l>
                  <l>And therfore I wolde be very glad, of hys companye.</l>
                  <l>In thys ſtayinge a whyle, at laſt he ouertoke me,</l>
                  <l>And with verye graue countenaunce, ſaluted me gentlye,</l>
                  <l>And with ſalutation, agayne I dyd hym grete,</l>
                  <l>As to my duetye, I thoughte it moſte mete.</l>
                  <l>Good father (and yf it pleaſe you) ſayde I,</l>
                  <l>Tell me, howe farre your iourney, this way doeth lye,</l>
                  <l>And of the ſame lye, anye thinge neare,</l>
                  <l>I wylbe very glad, you companye to be are,</l>
                  <l>For I haue, at thys tyme, lytle to do,</l>
                  <l>And woulde therfore, learne, ſome good counſayle of you.</l>
                  <l>And becauſe it is ſo, I am younge, and frayle,</l>
                  <l>And not as yet inſtructed, with wholſome counſayle,</l>
                  <l>My lyfe to directe, in tyme for to come,</l>
                  <l>Good leſſons, of you, I woulde learne ſome.</l>
                  <l>Whiche might cauſe me, for you, hereafter to praye,</l>
                  <l>When I ſhall folowe the ſame, an other daye,</l>
                  <l>Gentle ſonne, (quod he) the trueth to declare,</l>
                  <l>About ſoure myles hence, my iourney is to fare,</l>
                  <l>And becauſe I am aged, and maye not well go,</l>
                  <l>I take the mornynge with me, for it behoueth me ſo,</l>
                  <l>And backe agayne to nyght, homewarde, wyll I, yf I can,</l>
                  <l>Nyne myle a daye, is a great iourney, for an aged man,</l>
                  <l>Wherwith, I remembred my ſelfe, by and by,</l>
                  <l>And behelde the Sunne ſhyne, ſo gladſomely,</l>
                  <l>Cleare was the ſkye, and lightſome was the ayre,</l>
                  <l>And alſo the waye, ſented very fayre,</l>
                  <l>My buſynes, in dede (quod I) father, lyeth thre myle and more,</l>
                  <l>Along that waye, which ye muſt go, and therfore,</l>
                  <l>I wyl goe with you ſoftly, and make no great haſte,</l>
                  <l>For it requireth none, and this furth on we paſte,</l>
                  <l>God thancke you younge man, ſayde he: that ye are ſo kynde,</l>
                  <l>Since ye wyll go with me, and not leaue me behynde,</l>
                  <l>And becauſe your good wyll is, ſome wiſedome to lere,</l>
                  <l>The beſt counſayle I can geue, ye ſhall here,</l>
                  <l>And I wyll gladly, geue you the heringe (quod I)</l>
                  <l>Therfore when it ſhall pleaſe you, ſaye on by and by.</l>
                  <l>Firſt good ſonne, ye muſt to me make playne,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:4"/>
                  <l>Where is your dwellynge, and where ye remayne,</l>
                  <l>What ſtate ye are of, and of what diſpoſition,</l>
                  <l>And wherunto your mynde is geuen, in euery condition,</l>
                  <l>Alſo what is your name, ye muſte to me ſhewe,</l>
                  <l>And whether ye are ſyngle, or maried I woulde knowe,</l>
                  <l>Before, I can ſhewe you, my good abuiſe,</l>
                  <l>Or in any thynge prudently, enſtructe you otherwyſe.</l>
                  <l>Truely (quod I) my dwellynge, is not farre hence,</l>
                  <l>And to a worthye gentle man, of great reuerence,</l>
                  <l>Late ſeruaunt I was, but he is nowe deceaſſed,</l>
                  <l>Wherfore of ſeruyce, I am clearelye releaſed,</l>
                  <l>And touchynge myne age, I am younge it appeares,</l>
                  <l>As yet not paſſynge, one and twentye yeares,</l>
                  <l>Nitne ſaue truelye, moſt men call myne name,</l>
                  <l>Alſo ſingle, and vnmaried, as yet I remaine,</l>
                  <l>Well then, I perceyue (quod he) ye are yet yonge ynough,</l>
                  <l>In vertue to begynne, and ſo leade your lyfe through,</l>
                  <l>And alſo at libertie, and without a wyfe,</l>
                  <l>Nor as yet addicte, to any one kynde of lyfe,</l>
                  <l>Further as farre, as I maye or geſſe can,</l>
                  <l>Ye were lately as it were, a ſeruynge man,</l>
                  <l>Nowe whether it be, your mynde, and your wyll,</l>
                  <l>In the trade of ſeruyce, to continue ſtyll,</l>
                  <l>Or leaue of the ſame, and by ſome other meane,</l>
                  <l>To ſeke otherwayes, your liuinge to ſuſtayne,</l>
                  <l>Thys alſo to knowe, I earneſtlye require,</l>
                  <l>Or els, I can no waye, ſatiſfie your deſire,</l>
                  <l>In good fayth (ſayde I) ſo more I thrine,</l>
                  <l>A ſeruaunt I haue bene, aboute yeares fiue,</l>
                  <l>And truely haue ſerued to my power,</l>
                  <l>Since into ſeruice, I entered the fyrſt hower,</l>
                  <l>Wherin, there is ſo great, trauayle, and payne,</l>
                  <l>At moſte tymes, and ſo very lytle gayne,</l>
                  <l>And at other tymes alſo, ydlenes ſo greate,</l>
                  <l>Doinge nothynge, but ſettinge, in the feldes, and ſtreate,</l>
                  <l>Wherin, alſo there is muche great exerciſe,</l>
                  <l>Almoſte, of euery maner, and kinde of vice,</l>
                  <l>Bothe pride, dronckenneſſe, and alſo ſwearynge,</l>
                  <l>By abhominable others, God him ſelfe tearynge,</l>
                  <l>Suche quarrelynge, fighting, and other abhomination,</l>
                  <l>Wherof, I coulde make, vnto you true relation,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:5"/>
                  <l>Yf it were not odible, for you to heare,</l>
                  <l>As therperience therof, playnlye doeth appeare,</l>
                  <l>That I intende, vtterlye, the ſame to refuſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſome other, more godly ſtate, of lyuynge to chuſe,</l>
                  <l>Wherin I may, ſpende my tyme, more honeſtlie,</l>
                  <l>And in the feare of God, lyue more quietlie,</l>
                  <l>Without doubt (quod he) thou haſt ſayde trulye,</l>
                  <l>For beſydes, the foreſayde noughteneſſe, plentye</l>
                  <l>When a man hath, ſerued, a great tyme,</l>
                  <l>Yf he haue done, neuer ſo lytle a cryme,</l>
                  <l>Awaye he muſte, there is none other remedy,</l>
                  <l>Thus, is he put, to hys ſhiftes, by and by,</l>
                  <l>And put caſe, that he in ſeruyce continue,</l>
                  <l>Vntyll age come, that he can no more doe,</l>
                  <l>Then is he caſte of, either to begge hys breade,</l>
                  <l>Or in miſerye, to lyue, tyll tyme he be deade,</l>
                  <l>And euermore commonlye, it is ſene and harde.</l>
                  <l>Thys to be, of miſerable ſeruyce, the rewarde.</l>
                  <l>And to ſerue anye man, in the court of renowne,</l>
                  <l>You ſee, howe ſoone, they be vp, and downe,</l>
                  <l>But yf it ſhoulde chaunce you, as it doeth, to verye fewe,</l>
                  <l>Ye ſhoulde, ſo in your maiſters fauoure, hap to growe,</l>
                  <l>That he myght by ſome office, or other waye,</l>
                  <l>Get you any good lyuynge, ſome one daye,</l>
                  <l>Whiche is but a chaunce, and fortune ye maye it call,</l>
                  <l>For they gape them ſelues, for euerye windefall,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall he thynke you, ſtyl to hym bounde,</l>
                  <l>So longe as ye are lyuynge, on the grounde,</l>
                  <l>And yf it chaunce hym hereafter, the lawe to haue offended,</l>
                  <l>You alſo beynge hys man, are lyke to be apprehended,</l>
                  <l>Then haue ye well, and fayre fiſhed in dede,</l>
                  <l>Your ryſynge, was then, in more haſte, then good ſpede,</l>
                  <l>And ſome, wiſe men flee commonlye, ſuche lyuynge to ſeke,</l>
                  <l>Whiche is firſt ſo harde to come by, and after ſo il to kepe.</l>
                  <l>Wherfore, to applye thy youth, nomore in it,</l>
                  <l>I can not chuſe, but greatlye allowe, thy wit,</l>
                  <l>Nowe then (quod he) further, what other vocation,</l>
                  <l>Serueth thy mynde thee, or to what occupation,</l>
                  <l>To get thy lyuynge, either by trade of marchaundiſe,</l>
                  <l>Or by ſome handye crafte, or arte otherwiſe.</l>
                  <l>No (ſayde I) in marchaundiſe, I haue no ſkyll,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:5"/>
                  <l>Nor to ſpende my tyme, therin I wyll,</l>
                  <l>Foraſmuche, as the ſame, is ruled by chaunce,</l>
                  <l>Alſo, ſence I am ignoraunte therof, howe can it me auaunce,</l>
                  <l>And he that by marchandiſe, wyll get hys lyuynge,</l>
                  <l>Nedeth bothe good credit, and a ſtocke at the begynnynge,</l>
                  <l>But in me lacketh bothe, for ſtocke haue I none,</l>
                  <l>And becauſe I was once a ſeruynge man, my credit is gone,</l>
                  <l>Fewe merchauntes wyll truſte, any of that race,</l>
                  <l>Althoughe it were neuer in ſo honeſt a cace,</l>
                  <l>Beſydes that, I muſt ſwere, perioure, and lye,</l>
                  <l>If I wyll, byinge and ſellynge occupie,</l>
                  <l>My wares, muſt be nowe and then, alſo counterfet,</l>
                  <l>If I intende, by them, anye gayne to get,</l>
                  <l>Throughe which I ſhall, diſpleaſe God, and ſynne,</l>
                  <l>Thus doinge, I ſhal, a fayre threde ſpynne,</l>
                  <l>I wyll rather diſpiſe, ſuche vnhappye wynnynge,</l>
                  <l>As wyll brynge me to hell, at the firſt begynnynge,</l>
                  <l>You ſaye well, (quod he) and beſydes all thys,</l>
                  <l>To be a marchaunt, ſonne, another thynge there is,</l>
                  <l>For many marchauntes, of late in thys lande,</l>
                  <l>Haue bene vndone, and brought behynde hande,</l>
                  <l>Whiche neuer coulde, after agayne aryſe,</l>
                  <l>Suche is the bryttell ſtate, of marchaundiſe,</l>
                  <l>Alſo, ſayde I, in any other handye crafte, or ſcience,</l>
                  <l>Trulye to confeſſe, I haue none entelligence,</l>
                  <l>And thoughe I had, yet is the worlde, nowe in ſuche penury,</l>
                  <l>That almoſte no kynde of craftes man, can lyue therby</l>
                  <l>All kynde of thynges, are nowe waxen ſo dere,</l>
                  <l>That the lyke hath not bene ſene, thys manye a yere,</l>
                  <l>I wyll tell you, (quod he) ſence tyme, I was borne,</l>
                  <l>And I ſhal be iuſte. lxxx. yeare olde, come to morne,</l>
                  <l>Was neuer, ſuche miſery, neceſſitie, and nede.</l>
                  <l>Amongeſt eche eſtate, in euerye ſtede,</l>
                  <l>As is euen nowe, at thys preſente daye,</l>
                  <l>For though, diuerſe tymes paſt, as I ſaye</l>
                  <l>Corne hath bene, as dere, here before,</l>
                  <l>Yet of all other thynges, we had plentye and ſtore,</l>
                  <l>But nowe, the price of all thynges, hath lepte, ſuche a leape,</l>
                  <l>That nother, fode, clothing, nor any other thing, is good cheape,</l>
                  <l>In whome the faulte is, truly I can not tell,</l>
                  <l>But I woulde to God, that all thynge were well,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:6"/>
                  <l>And I tell you younge man, in good earneſt,</l>
                  <l>I heartely thancke, my redemer Chriſt,</l>
                  <l>That my hoore head, is ſo neare vnto the graue,</l>
                  <l>My unſerye, ſhalbe the ſhorter, that I fele, and haue,</l>
                  <l>But concernynge, our firſte communication,</l>
                  <l>It ſemeth, your mynde is, to none occupation,</l>
                  <l>What then, haue ye good learnynge, any whitte,</l>
                  <l>Perchaunce, to be a prieſt, ye thyncke your ſelfe fitte,</l>
                  <l>And ſurely (quod he) yf your callynge be ſo wel,</l>
                  <l>Then ye do amiſſe, neuer a del,</l>
                  <l>For to preache, truely Gods worde, and be a miniſter,</l>
                  <l>Yf your callynge be therunto, ye can not do better,</l>
                  <l>Certaynlye (quod I) my learnynge is but ſmall,</l>
                  <l>And to great a matter, it is, for me to medle withall,</l>
                  <l>Well learned he ſhoulde be, and of Gods callynge,</l>
                  <l>That ſhoulde occupie, the place of preachynge,</l>
                  <l>But I am bothe verye vnlearned truelye,</l>
                  <l>And alſo farre vnmete, that place to occupye,</l>
                  <l>You ſaye well (quod he) for ye myght, worke your ſelfe wo,</l>
                  <l>Yf ye woulde attempte, in at the windowe to go,</l>
                  <l>Or leape ouer the ſhepecote, not called by God,</l>
                  <l>So might you make, for your owne tayle a rod,</l>
                  <l>With almightie God (ſonne) is not good, to playe,</l>
                  <l>For he may not, be dallied with, by no waye,</l>
                  <l>Ye might therby, he ape Gods vengeaunce, to you, for your haſt,</l>
                  <l>And eternall dampnation, perchaunce, at the laſt,</l>
                  <l>To be a lawier, then (quod he) perchaunce, is thy deſire,</l>
                  <l>Therby, thou thynckeſt, to great ryches, to aſpire,</l>
                  <l>Not ſo (quod I) for ſome learnynge, I doe lacke,</l>
                  <l>Nor neuer, of Sophiſtrie, or Lodgike, had the ſmacke,</l>
                  <l>By whiche ſtandeth the chiefeſt, and principall poynte,</l>
                  <l>As of that, pleadinge ſcience, the beſt ioynte,</l>
                  <l>All thinges conſidered, I mynde not that art.</l>
                  <l>Nor euer, hither, coulde it ſtande with my harte,</l>
                  <l>Certaynelye, ſayde he, the lawe is good, if it be well vſed,</l>
                  <l>But nowe, the iuſtice, of the ryght lawe, is ſomwhat abuſed,</l>
                  <l>And manye of their riſynge, is by extortion.</l>
                  <l>Wherby, they clinte, to haue, of riches, ſuch portion,</l>
                  <l>And through the ſame, they almoſte are growne, to like obliquie,</l>
                  <l>As the Clergie, at the firſt fal, were wont to be,</l>
                  <l>And not without a very vrgent cauſe,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:6"/>
                  <l>They doe, ſome without right, ſo writhe, &amp; wreſt the lawes,</l>
                  <l>And (ſonne) in my iudgement, to be playne,</l>
                  <l>Much of their lawe, tendeth to their owne gayne.</l>
                  <l>Wel, then I thincke, ye wyl beyonde the ſea go,</l>
                  <l>Your youth in learning, to occupye ſo,</l>
                  <l>For ſouth (quod I) of al the reſt I fynde</l>
                  <l>That this moſt pleaſinge, to my mynde,</l>
                  <l>Yf ſo it were, my liuinge woulde extende,</l>
                  <l>There to kepe me, two or thre yeares to an ende,</l>
                  <l>Wherby I myght, though it were to my payne,</l>
                  <l>Se countreyes, and ſome knowledge obtayne,</l>
                  <l>But he that goeth thyther, without a good purſe,</l>
                  <l>Goeth out of Goddes bleſſinge, into hys curſe,</l>
                  <l>It is good for ſuch men, to go ouer truelye,</l>
                  <l>As entende, the kinges embaſſatours to be,</l>
                  <l>His graces waightie affaires, there for to do,</l>
                  <l>But I am not lyke, to come therto</l>
                  <l>The trueth for to ſay, and to be playne.</l>
                  <l>Since there is ſo much haſarde, and ſo ſmall gayne,</l>
                  <l>I am not as yet, mynded in thys care,</l>
                  <l>To ſeke my lyuynge, in ſo farre a place,</l>
                  <l>Therfore (quod the aged man) I agre,</l>
                  <l>For yf ye lacke there, ye ſhal fall in great miſerie,</l>
                  <l>And litle boteth, you ther, to ſerue anye man then,</l>
                  <l>For they are all, other flawes, or gentle men,</l>
                  <l>Further (ſayde he) what wilt thou then applie,</l>
                  <l>To lyue in the countreye, by thy lande or annuitie,</l>
                  <l>As perchaunce thou haſt, which I doe not knowe,</l>
                  <l>Tel me, that I may, thee, my beſt counſayle ſhewe,</l>
                  <l>I haue not (quod I) muche liuinge truelye,</l>
                  <l>But that which I haue, lyeth in the countreye,</l>
                  <l>Whervpon, I wyl, yf God hys helpe ſende,</l>
                  <l>Quietly liue, and there my lift ende,</l>
                  <l>Nowe I perceaue (quod he) thine hole entente,</l>
                  <l>In aringe thee, queſtions, this time haue I ſpente,</l>
                  <l>Therfore nowe I wyll ſhewe thee, in al that I can,</l>
                  <l>My counſayle, how thou mayeſt beſt proue, an honeſt man,</l>
                  <l>Say on (quod I) let vs no lenger tyme waſte,</l>
                  <l>For ſince we began, a good way haue we paſte,</l>
                  <l>My ſonne (ſayde he) thou ſemeſt verye wiſe,</l>
                  <l>That in thys laſt caſe, thy ſelfe doeſt aduiſe,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:7"/>
                  <l>Fyrſt God, and godly thynges, I wyl to thee preache,</l>
                  <l>And after in worldly thinges, to my power I wyl thee teache.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE principalleſt thynge, wherin thou muſte entende,</l>
                  <l>Is to haue good reſpecte, alwayes to the ende,</l>
                  <l>Wherfore, and why, God thee dyd create,</l>
                  <l>And howe, he hath appoynted thee, and in what eſtate,</l>
                  <l>For to thende, of thy fyrſte creacion,</l>
                  <l>Directe thy lyfe, in euery condicion,</l>
                  <l>Sonne, God brought thee, into the worlde here,</l>
                  <l>For two good cauſes, as it ſhall appere,</l>
                  <l>Fyrſte, to geue hym thanckes, laude, honour, and glorie,</l>
                  <l>And euermore, to prayſe hys eternall maieſtie,</l>
                  <l>Aſwel, for that it pleaſed hym, thee to forme and make,</l>
                  <l>And al thinges earthly, to create for thy ſake,</l>
                  <l>As alſo, for that, when thou were loſt, by Adams gilte,</l>
                  <l>He woulde not, of hys meare mercy, ſee thee ſpilte,</l>
                  <l>But ſent hys deare ſonne, from hys hygh troue,</l>
                  <l>Into thys wretched worlde, to redeme vs euery one,</l>
                  <l>Where, he toke vpon hym, our nature frayle,</l>
                  <l>In the bleſſed virgens wombe, for our auayle,</l>
                  <l>And then, here in earth, vs thirty yeares taughte,</l>
                  <l>By his worde, and miracles, which he wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully wroughte,</l>
                  <l>And at laſt, on the croſſe, ſuffred hys bitter paſſion,</l>
                  <l>Onely to redeme vs, and to obtayne cleane remiſſion,</l>
                  <l>Whiche, his mercy, yf it had not bene the greater,</l>
                  <l>We had remayned, dampned ſoules, and no better,</l>
                  <l>For thys cauſe, we are bounde him alwayes to prayſe,</l>
                  <l>For from death, ſynne, and hel, he agayne, dyd vs rayſe,</l>
                  <l>Therfore, him to prayſe, praye vnto, &amp; wurſhyp with feare,</l>
                  <l>Thys, ſtedfaſtly, in thy mynde, ſee that thou beare,</l>
                  <l>For it is the chiefeſt poynt, of vertue, to laude, and knowe,</l>
                  <l>The creation, of men, and al thynges, that growe,</l>
                  <l>Without thys, other vertues, are nothynge regarded,</l>
                  <l>In lackynge, thys pitie, thou ſhalte be lytle rewarded,</l>
                  <l>For thys, to all vertues, is thentrye ful playne,</l>
                  <l>Sence, by prayer onely, eche good thyng, of God we obtayne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE other cauſe, why God thee hyther broughte,</l>
                  <l>Was that thou ſhouldeſt, in worde, worke, and thoughte,</l>
                  <l>Alwayes endeuour, thy ſelfe to thy power,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:7"/>
                  <l>Hys holye commaundementes, to obaye, euery houre,</l>
                  <l>Whiche becauſe, I thincke, thou doeſt ſufficientlye knowe,</l>
                  <l>It nedeth not me, to repete them, on a rowe,</l>
                  <l>For theſe two cauſes, ſpecially, my dere ſonne,</l>
                  <l>God, into the worlde, cauſed thee, to come,</l>
                  <l>Theſe firme foundacions, fixed, once in thyne harte,</l>
                  <l>Then iuſtice rightlye to embrace, ſee thou doe thy parte,</l>
                  <l>Suffering no man, to ſuſtayne, any iniury by thee,</l>
                  <l>Or to hurt any creature, by dede, or worde, ſee thou flee,</l>
                  <l>And ſo do, to other men, of eche eſtate, and degree,</l>
                  <l>As thou wouldeſt, haue all men, ſhoulde do vnto thee,</l>
                  <l>For this lawe, of dame Nature, euery other lawe, doth excell,</l>
                  <l>Which, yf thou obſerue not, in euery poynt, well,</l>
                  <l>Truſt me truly (good ſonne) bothe the Lorde, thou ſhalt offende,</l>
                  <l>And in heauen, haue no habitarion, at thy lyues ende,</l>
                  <l>Further, any man, for hys honour, his goodes, or good name,</l>
                  <l>Beware, thou hate, not by malice, or diſdayne,</l>
                  <l>Alſo be circumſpecte, that neither bribes, hate or loue,</l>
                  <l>Thy heart, from equitie, and iuſtice, do remoue,</l>
                  <l>For theſe thre thinges, we ſee, ſo blindeth many mens ſighte,</l>
                  <l>That their iudgementes, and doinges, are contrary, to right,</l>
                  <l>But thou (my ſonne) remembre, that once thou ſhalt die,</l>
                  <l>And for theſe dedes, yf thou do them, be puniſhed, eternallie,</l>
                  <l>Alſo, the wicked thirſtinge, riches to obtayne,</l>
                  <l>And the vngodly coueting, of ſiluer, golde, and other gayne,</l>
                  <l>Se thou alſo ertue, for where couetouſnes, doth raygne,</l>
                  <l>There al kynde of wickednes, of force muſt remayne,</l>
                  <l>Impietie, periurie, rapine, and theuynge,</l>
                  <l>Fraude, crafte, and diſceate, with lecherous lyuynge,</l>
                  <l>Quarellynge, &amp; treaſons, with murders, and kyllynge,</l>
                  <l>For landes, treaſures, and goodes, many men, ſpillynge,</l>
                  <l>Finallye, no filthier thinge is there, or more deteſtable I ſay,</l>
                  <l>Then a man to be couetouſe, by any maner of way,</l>
                  <l>For whoſo to that vile vice, is once geuen,</l>
                  <l>To the blynde Mole, I maye him wel lyken,</l>
                  <l>Which neither loueth, deſireth, or any way knoweth,</l>
                  <l>Any other thynge, then in thys vayne worlde, groweth,</l>
                  <l>The wretche doth not ſee, howe ſhorte and how frayle,</l>
                  <l>The life of man is, and how death doth vs aſſayle,</l>
                  <l>Daylye ready, to ſtrike vs, his bowe being bente,</l>
                  <l>With his deadly, doubtfull darte, then is to late, to repente,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:8"/>
                  <l>He nother ſpareth, the younge, the olde, or any degre,</l>
                  <l>The riche, the learned, or the man in auctorytie,</l>
                  <l>The Lawer, the Landlorde, or the lacking poore man, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wepith,</l>
                  <l>But withoute any difference, he euery man ſtryketh,</l>
                  <l>And he is ofterymes nereſt vs, we dailie doo ſee,</l>
                  <l>When we mooſte, thincke him, furtheſt of too bee,</l>
                  <l>But then (my ſonne) theſe wordlie ryches here,</l>
                  <l>And theſe vaine goodes, ſubiecte, to blinde fortunes power,</l>
                  <l>Doo lytill eſteme, nor moche for them care,</l>
                  <l>For theſe thinges, are none of thyne, whatſoeuer they are,</l>
                  <l>Which either, vnſtable fortune, hir pleaſure too fulfill,</l>
                  <l>Doth geue, graunte, and plucke awaye, at hir variable will,</l>
                  <l>Or which, when thou dyeſt, will no lenger abyde,</l>
                  <l>But to ſeke them newe maiſters, awaye ſoudainly thei doo ſlyde</l>
                  <l>There bee other goodes, which thou oughteſt too acquyze,</l>
                  <l>And morche better ryches, thou ſhouldeſt deſyre,</l>
                  <l>Which with thee alwayes will remaine, and endure,</l>
                  <l>Of whom neither fortune, nor death, hath power be thou ſure</l>
                  <l>Theſe, ought thou too heape vp, for the, night and daye,</l>
                  <l>Then, in dede arte thou happie, and riche, euerye waie,</l>
                  <l>As for the reſte, which the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people, followe, and magnifie,</l>
                  <l>Yf thou haue them, as landes, goodes, catailles, or moneye,</l>
                  <l>Lawfullie vſe the ſame, no man can forbide thee,</l>
                  <l>But thou oughteſt to vſe them, with Iuſtice, and modeſtie,</l>
                  <l>And alſo when thou maieſt, pytie the pouertie,</l>
                  <l>And neuer ſhutte thine eares, at the crye of the nedie,</l>
                  <l>For who ſo with compaſſion, wil not hear, the crieng of the poore</l>
                  <l>Shal crye him ſelf, and not be heard, I am ſure,</l>
                  <l>By releuinge the poore, thou laieſt vp in ſtoore,</l>
                  <l>A treaſure, in heauen, to continue euermore,</l>
                  <l>Which neither canere can corrupte, neither theues, them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uaie,</l>
                  <l>Thus heauely treaſure, for worldly trifles, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt haue another daye</l>
                  <l>No man he is, but a Wulfe, that clemencye lacketh,</l>
                  <l>And which, at other mens myſerie, no pitie taketh,</l>
                  <l>Or that refuſeth too helpe, his fellowe ſeruaunte here,</l>
                  <l>Seinge wee are all ſeruauntes, to one Lorde, and maiſter,</l>
                  <l>But of it ſhall happen the (I ſaye) a poore man too bee,</l>
                  <l>With pacient hearte, beare, and ſuſtame, the pouertie</l>
                  <l>For the man, that hath moche, wee alwaye well ſee,</l>
                  <l>Is troubled, and toſſed, with cares, aboundauntlie,</l>
                  <l>Alſo he, to whom fortune, hath of goodes geuen ſtoore,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:8"/>
                  <l>The hote haſtye heate, beginneth to aſwage,</l>
                  <l>Then after fally, foloweth, frownynge, frowarde, repentaunce.</l>
                  <l>With ſorow, and ſhame faſtnes, bringing great greuaunce,</l>
                  <l>Therfore buſily beware of it, and thy mynde ſo moderate,</l>
                  <l>That this foule vyce, in thy corage, thou dilygently abate,</l>
                  <l>Pacience, is a vertue, of a wonderful ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>And obtayneth, the victory, of eche thing at length,</l>
                  <l>The which godly gyft, who ſo euer doth wante,</l>
                  <l>In hym all goodnes, and grace, of force, muſt be ſcante,</l>
                  <l>And cruel he muſt nedes he, and alſo to ſtrife, ful prone,</l>
                  <l>Which is not the nature, of man, but of beaſtes alone,</l>
                  <l>The prudent, and good, ſeketh chiefely for peaſſe,</l>
                  <l>And fearing greater miſchie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s, wyll beare with the leſſe,</l>
                  <l>Leſt, that a lytle ſparke, might encreaſe ſuch a flame,</l>
                  <l>That great peryl it were, agayne, to quenche the ſame,</l>
                  <l>He that nothing wyll ſuffre, nor his way warde wrath refrayne,</l>
                  <l>Muſt flee, the company, of al men we ſee playne,</l>
                  <l>And dwel alone, in the wodes, or mountaynes on hye,</l>
                  <l>Where no man, may trouble hym, nor he no body,</l>
                  <l>But he, that wyll frequent, and dwel amongeſt men,</l>
                  <l>Muſt learne, to ſuffer, dyſpleaſures, now and then,</l>
                  <l>And brydle hys furye, diſſemblynge his yre,</l>
                  <l>And in his ſecrete breſt, quench the hote fyre,</l>
                  <l>Nor in any wyſe may, for euery lyght offence,</l>
                  <l>Violate the bondes, of peace, and pacience,</l>
                  <l>But aſmuch as he can, forgiue other men,</l>
                  <l>That he offendynge in lyke caſe, may be alſo forgeuen,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ Further, Gloton ye to ertue, be euer circumſpecte,</l>
                  <l>Which with diuerſe diſeaſes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde, and body doth infecie,</l>
                  <l>Beſydes ſhortenynge mans lyfe, it conſumeth his wealth,</l>
                  <l>Vnwarely, as it were, him robbynge by ſtealth,</l>
                  <l>For dainties, are dere, and dilicates, be coſtely,</l>
                  <l>Swallowing vp cleane, great riches, quickely,</l>
                  <l>Some men, very rich, by prodigal ſuperfluitie,</l>
                  <l>Haue in ſhort time, deuoured their patrimonie,</l>
                  <l>Dayly pourynge in their bellyes, both houſe, goods, and lande,</l>
                  <l>Tyll pouertye them pincheth, and they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> broughte behande,</l>
                  <l>I haue knowen, very many, I tel the good ſonne,</l>
                  <l>That by laciniouſe ryotte, haue bene vtterly vndone,</l>
                  <l>Thou muſt eate (I ſaye) thy lyfe onely to ſuſtayne,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:9"/>
                  <l>And not lyue, to eate, this is moſt playne,</l>
                  <l>Ebreite and drunckennes, is alſo exceſſes brother,</l>
                  <l>For in whome, rayneth the one, there is alſo the other,</l>
                  <l>This likewyſe muſt thou fle, yf thou loue thy welfare,</l>
                  <l>Of al other the ſame, is the moſt deteſtable ſnare,</l>
                  <l>He that this wicked vyce, hath once embraced,</l>
                  <l>All goodnes in him, is clearly defaced,</l>
                  <l>Reaſon then refuſeth hym, and he is left too his wyll,</l>
                  <l>Al ſynnes haue free entraunce, him then for too ſpyll,</l>
                  <l>Good ſonne, I haue ſayd many yeres paſt,</l>
                  <l>That great Alerander in his drunckennes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in haſt,</l>
                  <l>His moſt deare and familiare frendes to be ſlayne,</l>
                  <l>By whoſe helpe and good counſayle as it is mooſt playne,</l>
                  <l>He had the hole world conquered, who beynge thus dedde,</l>
                  <l>And ſlepe had expulſed ebriety out of Alexanders hedde,</l>
                  <l>He then ſo lamented their deathes in wepynge bytterlye,</l>
                  <l>That he was redy for very anguyſhe to dye preſentlye,</l>
                  <l>Oh fylthy ebrietie, the deſtroyer of the ſoule,</l>
                  <l>Oh noryſher of vyces, and iniquities all,</l>
                  <l>What thing is it, but thou forceſt mannes harte, to fulfyll,</l>
                  <l>Wherby he wareth bolde, too attempt all that is yll,</l>
                  <l>Quarellynge, ſtryfe, cruel fraies, thou doeſt moue,</l>
                  <l>Neyther, regardynge diſcrecion, honeſt frendſhip, or loue,</l>
                  <l>Through the counſaile is opened, and ſecrettis reueled,</l>
                  <l>The tongue is not then hable, too kepe the ſame cloſed,</l>
                  <l>Flee this vyce, my ſonne, in all that thou maye,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt it growe, from cuſtome, too nature another daye,</l>
                  <l>The tongue alſo, thou muſt learne too moderate,</l>
                  <l>And be well ware, what thou ſpeakeſt early and late,</l>
                  <l>Be euermore wyllynge, attentify too heare,</l>
                  <l>But ſpeake ſeldome, as nede ſhall require,</l>
                  <l>Aboundaunce of talke, is a great ſygne of follye,</l>
                  <l>And the buſye babler, offendeth continuallye,</l>
                  <l>He that ſeldome talketh, and then ſpeaketh wyſelye,</l>
                  <l>Is worthye much prayſe, and approueth too be wittie,</l>
                  <l>One principal point, obſerue in thy communication,</l>
                  <l>Whether they be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or abſent, w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thy words hurt no man,</l>
                  <l>Nor except it tende too ſome purpoſe, ſpeake thou any thing,</l>
                  <l>Leaſte men laughe the too ſcorne, for thy bablynge,</l>
                  <l>Rather holde thy peace, and be euer ſilent,</l>
                  <l>It hurteth not, neyther ſhall it thee repent,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:9"/>
                  <l>In daunger, and perell, he remayneth euermore,</l>
                  <l>Experience doth teach vs, and we ſee euery daye,</l>
                  <l>Some mans landes, and ryches, too be their caſtynge away,</l>
                  <l>It is no newe thynge, to ſee this abuſion,</l>
                  <l>That dyuerſe mennes wealthes, haue bene theyr confuſion,</l>
                  <l>Alſo riche men, are w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the burde of their goodes ſo borne downe,</l>
                  <l>That they haue no minde, to ſeke, after the celeſtial manſion,</l>
                  <l>For the more, a man deſyreth, riches, and earthly gayne,</l>
                  <l>So much the harder, it is, for him, too heauen to attayne,</l>
                  <l>For looke, where a mans treaſure is layde,</l>
                  <l>There is alſo hys harte, it can not bee denayed,</l>
                  <l>Therefore, pouertye, to ſome perſons, is profytable,</l>
                  <l>Diſburdenynge them, of miſcheffes innumerable.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>FVRTHER, pride, of thee, is to be abhorred no leſſe,</l>
                  <l>Beynge of ſtryfe, and debate, the mother, and miſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>By this, the lawes, ar neglected, and the common welth ſpylled,</l>
                  <l>And innumerable people, this vayne pryde, hath kylled,</l>
                  <l>With this peſtilence, the famouſe Rome being once poyſoned,</l>
                  <l>By cyuill warre, and oppreſſion, was vtterly deſtroyed,</l>
                  <l>This monſtruous helhound, by alway ſee thou flee,</l>
                  <l>Yf thou wylt with almyghty God, lyue eternallye,</l>
                  <l>For God, in the lowly, and meke, taketh delectacion,</l>
                  <l>And in the humble ſpirites, glady hath his habitacion,</l>
                  <l>Them alſo, he fauoureth, that are voyde of ambicion,</l>
                  <l>And the proud, ſwellynge people, he bringeth to confution,</l>
                  <l>Therefore ye people, puft vp with pryde, what profyteth you,</l>
                  <l>Your pride, high names, and vayne ſtyles, forged newe,</l>
                  <l>Which death, doth confounde, and bringeth in ſubieccion,</l>
                  <l>Your ambiſious tytels, of ſo great a renowne,</l>
                  <l>Some wyll perchaunce ſay, the common people, we wil pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>In couetynge of them, therfore to haue our prayſe,</l>
                  <l>Tel me (I praye you) what is the iudgement, of the multytude,</l>
                  <l>Ye ſhall perceaue many tymes, they doo mocke and delude,</l>
                  <l>Or elles ſpeake of affeccion, as ſome tyme, namynge them wyſe,</l>
                  <l>Which are perchaunce, very fooles, rightly to ſurmyſe,</l>
                  <l>And though, the ignoraunt we mocke, God can we not deceaue,</l>
                  <l>Naye, he rather derydeth vs by our leaue,</l>
                  <l>For he knoweth our maners, and our dedes, moſt ſecrete,</l>
                  <l>And for them worthelye to punyſhe vs he wil not forget,</l>
                  <l>But many, are ſo blynde, that in their owne thoughte,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:10"/>
                  <l>They beleue, there is no God, &amp; that there remayneth nought</l>
                  <l>Of any man, the breathe, beynge once erpired,</l>
                  <l>Therfore, the preſent ioyes, of this lyfe, they haue euer deſyred,</l>
                  <l>And do dayly wyſhe for, deridynge the bliſſe to come,</l>
                  <l>Haue not they, beſtial heartes, vnder mans ſhape and forme,</l>
                  <l>We ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke after ryches our pride too mayntayne,</l>
                  <l>Oure lyfe vanely ſpendynge to ſeke a ſynfull gayne,</l>
                  <l>We ponder not the frayltye of our wretched ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Weſe not death dayly redy, our pryde to abate,</l>
                  <l>We are ſo contentleſſe from moſte vnto leaſte,</l>
                  <l>That in oure vocacion we neuer can reſte,</l>
                  <l>Wel yf in worldly thynges blynde fortunes gouernaunce,</l>
                  <l>Ruled not without reaſon at hir owne wil and pleaſaunce,</l>
                  <l>As we ſe ſhe dothe, then all thinges ſhould be wel,</l>
                  <l>The lawes, and iuſtice, ſhould floryſhe, and tiranny expel,</l>
                  <l>But ſince almighty God, ſuffereth ſuch thinges to be done.</l>
                  <l>Who if it pleaſed hym, coulde amende al right ſoone,</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould we grutche, to ſuffer the ſame,</l>
                  <l>To repyne, at Gods wyl, we are greatly to blame,</l>
                  <l>Wherfore, wyſedom willeth wyſe men, euer to be patient,</l>
                  <l>And taking al thinges, as it commeth, to be content,</l>
                  <l>But thou (my ſonne) endeuour thy ſelfe, in al that thou can,</l>
                  <l>Blynde fortune to diſpyce, and the vayne prayſe of man,</l>
                  <l>Onely ſtudye thou dayly, by al maner of wayes,</l>
                  <l>With vertuouſe lyuynge, the Lord for to pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>For true honour, and prayſe, thou canſt not obtayne,</l>
                  <l>Vntyl after this lyfe, in heauen thou remayne,</l>
                  <l>Whiche the good, and iuſte, ſhal enioy there,</l>
                  <l>That with humblenes, and mekeneſſe, haue led their lyfe here,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>ALSO, I charge thee, thyne angre to ſuppreſſe,</l>
                  <l>And the hote rage, of ire, which cauſeth great buſyneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Wrathe, worketh wo, and much miſchiefe we ſee,</l>
                  <l>Furye, maketh frayes, and then of neceſſitie,</l>
                  <l>Foloweth wyde woundes, hurtes and other mayme,</l>
                  <l>In which bluddy bickeringes, oft tyines ſome men are ſlayne,</l>
                  <l>For the mynde of man, beynge once, incenſed with ire,</l>
                  <l>Is ſo blyndely oppreſſed, with that raſhe, ragynge fyre,</l>
                  <l>That it neyther can beholde, or iudge any thing a ryght,</l>
                  <l>Reaſon then ruleth not, and wit hath loſt his myght,</l>
                  <l>When after once beynge paſt, ſuch furiouſe rage,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:10"/>
                  <l>Too haue bene quiet, and ſtill, but erperience teacheth,</l>
                  <l>That the talkatiue perſon, oft to his paine repenteth,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>FINALLY my ſonne, a nother thing ther is,</l>
                  <l>Which I haue not to the yet, reherſed ywys,</l>
                  <l>That aboue all the reſt, thy lyfe will deface,</l>
                  <l>If in youth too repreſſe it, thou haue not the grace,</l>
                  <l>That is the wanton deſyres, of the bodie frayle,</l>
                  <l>With this thy beſt age, will violentlie aſſaile,</l>
                  <l>The lewd luſtes wherof, ſee that thou flee,</l>
                  <l>And brydle thou them, before they blind thee,</l>
                  <l>Ther is no thinge too vertue, ſoo cleane contrarye,</l>
                  <l>As is the wicked concupiſcence, of the bodie,</l>
                  <l>Wher vertue too the heauens, ſtriueth too aſſende,</l>
                  <l>Vyle luſte, vaine pleaſures, onlie doth attende,</l>
                  <l>Lokinge alwaies, as a beaſt too the earth grouelinge.</l>
                  <l>The liue lie ſprites, both of the minde, and bodie diſtroyenge,</l>
                  <l>The deuill taketh manie, with his booke and ſnare,</l>
                  <l>Like a craftie ſore, no trauell doth he ſpare,</l>
                  <l>So he may withhold them, the bliſſe of heauen too attaine,</l>
                  <l>And after this life, within in hell, too liue euer with paine,</l>
                  <l>Theſe deceates therfore, of Sathan thin enemie,</l>
                  <l>And this deteſtable poyſon, couered ouer with honye,</l>
                  <l>Warely beware of, as moche as thou maye,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt the ſame repent the, in vaine a nother daye,</l>
                  <l>When thy rype yeres, of diſcretion, and mans perfect ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Shall clearlie perceaue, all thoughe then to late,</l>
                  <l>Thy wytte, thy ſubſtaunce, members, and good name,</l>
                  <l>By a lytill wanton pleaſure, conſumed to remane,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhalt thou, as many other ar wont too ſaie,</l>
                  <l>Oh youth, and luſtye yeares, howe ar yee vanyſhed awaye,</l>
                  <l>Howe euill haue I ſpente you wretche that I am,</l>
                  <l>Whether are ye gone, oh vnfortunate man,</l>
                  <l>Yf god of his goodnes, wold eſtſones reſtore,</l>
                  <l>The ioyfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>uentute, I once had before,</l>
                  <l>If I might once I ſaye the ſame againe ebtaine,</l>
                  <l>I wold then tread, the right pathe, of vertue ſoo plaine,</l>
                  <l>Although the ſame were, neuer ſo narowe a waye,</l>
                  <l>I wolde therein walke, and continue night and daye,</l>
                  <l>That there is no thing like vertue, I finde nowe full true,</l>
                  <l>Nor to it, too bee compared, this alas ofte doo I rue,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:11"/>
                  <l>Whiche euer continueth, and alwaye doth endure,</l>
                  <l>Geuing to man, ſuche worthy prayſe, &amp; honor as is ſure,</l>
                  <l>She increaſeth thy ryches, and thy lyfe doth preſerue,</l>
                  <l>Yea after death, ſhe abiding, away wyl not ſwarue,</l>
                  <l>But I of all other, thincke my ſelfe moſt vnhappye,</l>
                  <l>Who by flatteringe voluptuouſnes, was dereaued wylfullye,</l>
                  <l>Which ſlidying away, longe ſince hath lefte me,</l>
                  <l>Wrapped in al my miſchiefes, and wofull miſerye,</l>
                  <l>For I beinge a younge man, the ſtewes dyd frequente,</l>
                  <l>And in bancketinge, ſlepe, and play, my tyme ydlye ſpente,</l>
                  <l>Nothing then woulde I learne, all ſtudy I deſpiſed,</l>
                  <l>Abhorring in good ſcience, to be exerciſed,</l>
                  <l>But nowe therfore (we worth the tyine) I well ſee,</l>
                  <l>My ſelfe bothe vnlearned, and no leſſe di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>amed to be,</l>
                  <l>In pouertie alſo, and my whole body bruſed,</l>
                  <l>My wittes altogether dulled, and my ſences confuſed,</l>
                  <l>I haue hither to liued, as one who hath dreamed,</l>
                  <l>Him ſelfe to be awake, and yet was deceaued,</l>
                  <l>Suche thinges (ſonne) of ſome men, we are wonte for to here,</l>
                  <l>That are farre ſtricken in age, and to their graue draw nere.</l>
                  <l>Which callynge to remembraunce, their luſtye yeares paſt,</l>
                  <l>Do now (but to late) bewayle their miſerye at the laſt,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhuttinge the ſtable dore, when horſes there be none,</l>
                  <l>And now waring wiſe, when blinde Fortune is gone,</l>
                  <l>Then ſekyng a Surgion to heale their rancled ſore,</l>
                  <l>When there is no hope of cure, in the ſame any more,</l>
                  <l>My ſonne, therfore take tyme, whyle thou maye,</l>
                  <l>For it neuer retourneth, yf it once vaniſhe awaye,</l>
                  <l>Neither waylinge, wyl helpe, nor wepynge then remedye,</l>
                  <l>Yf the body be once ſtricken, with deathes darte deadlye.</l>
                  <l>The medicine is profitable, Phiciſione doe ſaye,</l>
                  <l>That in time is miniſtred, not ſlackyng any daye,</l>
                  <l>Wherfore when thyne youth, firſt to floryſhe doth begynne,</l>
                  <l>Then thee behoueth vertue to embrace, and fle from ſynne,</l>
                  <l>Then oughteſt thou to take, the ryght pathe of lyuynge,</l>
                  <l>To good and honeſt ſtudyes, thy ſelfe holly applyinge,</l>
                  <l>Then vſe thou reaſon, and gouerue by counſayle thy mynde,</l>
                  <l>While the ſame is pliaunte, euery waye to wynde,</l>
                  <l>Whoſo wylbe wyſe, let him be wyſe whyle he maye,</l>
                  <l>For to be wiſe a daye after the fayre, is folyſhnes I ſaye,</l>
                  <l>And therfore he is worthye, hys miſerye to ſuſtayne,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:11"/>
                  <l>Bewaylinge the loſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is neuer to be recouered agayne,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOWE touchinge this worlde, vnderſtande plainelye,</l>
                  <l>That the ſame is veary ſhort, and tranſitorie,</l>
                  <l>And the hole lyfe of man, wherein we do rurine,</l>
                  <l>In compariſon to theternite, of the woride to come,</l>
                  <l>The trueth wherof, to be truely declared,</l>
                  <l>To one momente of tyme, is not to be compared,</l>
                  <l>And touching the myſerye, of the worlde I ſaye,</l>
                  <l>He is happyer that is gone, then here farre awaye,</l>
                  <l>For marke I pray the, howe infancye cometh oute,</l>
                  <l>Of his mothers wombe naked, without any cloute,</l>
                  <l>And the firſt thinge he then doth, is wepinge with teares,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe the miſerie of this worlde, as I thincke he feares,</l>
                  <l>As I mighte it lyken, to ſome marchaunt man,</l>
                  <l>Which on ſome percellous vyage, his waye muſt take than,</l>
                  <l>And fearing both drowninge, Pirats, and ſhipwrake,</l>
                  <l>Tremblynge, ſo daungerous a iourney to take,</l>
                  <l>Eurn ſo, nature teacheth, the infaunte plainlye,</l>
                  <l>That he then entreth, into the vale of myſerie,</l>
                  <l>All other beaftes, that nature bringeth forthe,</l>
                  <l>To their da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes tytt, ronne ſtraight with open mouthe,</l>
                  <l>But man, as ſoone as euer he is borne,</l>
                  <l>Yf the mother, clothe, and fede him not, he is forlorne,</l>
                  <l>After Infauncie, how longe it is,</l>
                  <l>Or perceueraunce crepyth, in that lityll breſt of his,</l>
                  <l>Childhode cometh after, wherofneyther of them both,</l>
                  <l>Can by reaſon rule them ſelues, be they lefe or loth,</l>
                  <l>Then what grefe, trauayle, feare, and payne,</l>
                  <l>Suffreth the chylde, or he to iuuentute doth attayne,</l>
                  <l>Then ignoraunte fraill youth, begynneth to aryſe,</l>
                  <l>Which leaueth reaſon, and comonly is ruled by vyce,</l>
                  <l>His ſtrength encreaſinge, he putteth away feare,</l>
                  <l>Good warninges, and preceptes, he will then no more heare,</l>
                  <l>Then wareth he wilde, his younge bloud beinge warme,</l>
                  <l>Geuen to Ire, and Luſſe, which doth hym moch harme,</l>
                  <l>Good counſell he refuſeth, and is then raſhe in all thinge,</l>
                  <l>To the euill enclyned, the good euer ertuinge,</l>
                  <l>Noperel he doubteth, no daunger he doth refraine,</l>
                  <l>So that his fraill luſte, he may by anie meane obtaine,</l>
                  <l>No lawe he then feareth, yf there be a toye in his braine,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:12"/>
                  <l>Fewe younge men in that age, from vice can abſtaine,</l>
                  <l>Whom either ſhame faſtneſs, feare, or wiſdome, doth conſtraint,</l>
                  <l>By no ſpotte of vice, their youth for to ſtaine,</l>
                  <l>Then cometh mans ſtate, graue and ſage,</l>
                  <l>By erperience, and wiſdome, he is taught in this age.</l>
                  <l>Then vnſounde are his ſlepes, he lanboureth with paine,</l>
                  <l>The liuinge of him ſelfe, and his houſe to ſuſtaine,</l>
                  <l>He gathered together, in that ſtate of life,</l>
                  <l>In age to kepe hun, his famelie and wife,</l>
                  <l>Onelie caringe for them all, both to cloth and fede,</l>
                  <l>Spendinge this his beſt age, with miſerye in dede,</l>
                  <l>And then wearye rude age, on man faſt crepeth,</l>
                  <l>Stealinge vpon him, whether he waketh or ſleapeth,</l>
                  <l>Bringinge many diſcommodites, both of minde, and bodie,</l>
                  <l>His ſtrength taketh his leaue, his freſhe colour will not tarye</l>
                  <l>His ſences ſhrincke awaye, his ſight wareth dime,</l>
                  <l>His hearinge dulleth, and his ſmellinge leaueth hime,</l>
                  <l>Further he is alwaies vered, with one or other diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>No meate him then ſauourith, al thinge him diſpleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Withoute aide of a ſtafe, his legges him then fale,</l>
                  <l>His witte is then gone, his body ſhrincheth, waring pale,</l>
                  <l>This euery age, hath his infirmitie, we ſee,</l>
                  <l>Which of force, we are forced, to ſuffer parientlie,</l>
                  <l>Which laſt age, will not leaue him, til he hath broughte,</l>
                  <l>Man to his graue, where he conſumeth to noughte,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>ILET paſſe, of all other comon perrilles to tell,</l>
                  <l>With which man is beſeged, while he here doth dwell,</l>
                  <l>Wherwith a mans life, is ſo greately enuironed,</l>
                  <l>That it is ſeldome, or neuer, but by ſome of them deuoured,</l>
                  <l>Nowe vehemente colde, with I lye ſnowe greue vs,</l>
                  <l>Then hotte burninge heate, to vs are moleſtiouſe,</l>
                  <l>Thertremitie, whereof, as is ofte ſeene,</l>
                  <l>Cauſeth the ground, wyde open, ſome licoure to obtaine,</l>
                  <l>Sometyms we are noyed, by ſo greate wete, and raine,</l>
                  <l>That it ouer floweth, hole contries we ſe plaine,</l>
                  <l>Hunger, thirſt, and alſo moch penurie,</l>
                  <l>Wyth the wantyng, of neceſſarie thinges to occupie,</l>
                  <l>Who can declare, in miter, or in proſe,</l>
                  <l>The greate and manyſolde, nomber of thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Diſcaſes, and ſickeneſſes, of euery hinde,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:12"/>
                  <l>Which killeth daylie our bodies, and verith our minde,</l>
                  <l>By battel, and warfaire, ſome men are confounded,</l>
                  <l>In the ſeas, and other, waters, many men, are drowned,</l>
                  <l>Other ſome, by fallinge, catch theyr bane,</l>
                  <l>Orels by cruſhing, their members, are made lame,</l>
                  <l>Some men, cruell fyre, to aſhes doth conſume,</l>
                  <l>Many ar chocked, and cruell beaſtes killeth ſome,</l>
                  <l>What ſhal I recite, howe in earth, the liuing manne,</l>
                  <l>Hath no greater enemie, then the ſede wherof he came,</l>
                  <l>Of that ſede, ſpringeth, al theues, and robers,</l>
                  <l>All murderers, periured, and falſe witneſſe bearers,</l>
                  <l>Fornicatours alſo, and vile, adulterers,</l>
                  <l>And of mankinde diſcende, al wicked doers,</l>
                  <l>This ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with his weapon, another with his tongue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do kile,</l>
                  <l>The moſt parte, by fraude, and deceate, worketh ile,</l>
                  <l>O lorde, all men, almooſt nowe take delite,</l>
                  <l>At other mens harmes, ſuche is their ſpite,</l>
                  <l>The brother, the naturall brother, doth miſtruſt,</l>
                  <l>The amitie, of frendes, nowe lieth in the duſt,</l>
                  <l>The father, his ſonne, and the huſband his wife,</l>
                  <l>Eche ſuſpecte other, here is a goodly lyfe,</l>
                  <l>Nowe ſonne, I haue told the, aſwell as I can,</l>
                  <l>The perels, that doo compaſſe, the life of man,</l>
                  <l>Wherfore thou maieſt not, this worldelie pleaſure vſe</l>
                  <l>Ercept thou intende, eternell life to refuſe,</l>
                  <l>And the tyme veary ſhort, that thou here ſhalt remaine,</l>
                  <l>The trueth wherof, I can well declare plaine,</l>
                  <l>For all though that I am, nowe fowre ſcore yeare olde,</l>
                  <l>Yet the bedroll of my lyfe, when I do vnfolde,</l>
                  <l>I do nowe wel ponder, and perceaue in this caſe,</l>
                  <l>The ſame to haue ben, but a veary litil ſpace,</l>
                  <l>And yet to liue myne age, of a hunderith I knowe,</l>
                  <l>One ſhalt thou not finde, though thou ſought them on a rowe</l>
                  <l>Good father ſayde I, I thincke you ſaye true,</l>
                  <l>For I haue ſcene veary fewe, of thage of youe,</l>
                  <l>Nowe (quod he) I haue taughte you, ſufficientlie to knowe,</l>
                  <l>Firſt God, your ſelfe, and the worlde, I trowe,</l>
                  <l>And becauſe quietlie, your lyfe you wolde leade,</l>
                  <l>In the feare, and loue, of God, as ye ſaide,</l>
                  <l>I coulde wiſhe, you ſhould prudentlie prouyde,</l>
                  <l>Of ſome good ſtocke, a wife with you to abyde,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:13"/>
                  <l>By whome, ye ſhal, many comodites poſſeſſe,</l>
                  <l>More then I can, at this lyme, expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>For your wife, ſhall leaue, both father and mother,</l>
                  <l>To ſticke to you onely, and to none other,</l>
                  <l>Hyr owne kinred, and frendes doth ſhe leaue,</l>
                  <l>Dayelie, duringe hir lyfe, to you for to cleaue,</l>
                  <l>By hir, ſhall ye haue, fruite of your owne ſede</l>
                  <l>Which ſhal kepe you in remeinbraunce, whe tyme ye are dede,</l>
                  <l>Obedient, ſhe wilbe, and a ſurrour alwayes,</l>
                  <l>And a ioyfull ioye alſo, to prolonge your dayes,</l>
                  <l>Eche good thinge, ſhal be comon, euer you betwene,</l>
                  <l>Your games, ſhal be one, your lyuinges to ſuſtaine</l>
                  <l>Further, yf age, or ſicknes, ſhal greue you hereafter,</l>
                  <l>She wil be a contynuall, and faithfull helper,</l>
                  <l>By aſſiſtinge, miniſtrynge, and watchinge, you alſo,</l>
                  <l>Comfortinge, and releuinge you, with the beſt ſhe can do,</l>
                  <l>And then youre children, which hereafter may floriſhe,</l>
                  <l>Will do theyr indeuour, you gladely to cheriſhe,</l>
                  <l>In whom ye ſhal yet lyue, when life is gone cleane,</l>
                  <l>And your name ſtill on lyue, by them ſhall remane,</l>
                  <l>Further, to them ſhall ye leue, youre goodes being gotte,</l>
                  <l>And not vnto ſtraunge heires, which ye knowe not,</l>
                  <l>Beſides this, your wiſe, with hir ſome what wil bringe</l>
                  <l>Towarde the maintenaunce, of your and her liuinge,</l>
                  <l>Both frendes, and kinſefolke, by hir wil ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Which maye be to thee profytable, in ſondrye wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Wherfore, a wife you muſt haue, ther is none other naye,</l>
                  <l>Yf ye meane quietlie, and godlye to liue another daye,</l>
                  <l>Good father (quod I) me thinke ye ſaye well,</l>
                  <l>But of one thinge, I wolde gladlie heare tell,</l>
                  <l>Which waye were beſt, by your conſyderacyon,</l>
                  <l>Howe I myght, haue one, of an honeſt conuerſation,</l>
                  <l>Marye younge man (quod he) there lyeth al the matter,</l>
                  <l>In the wittle wiſdome, of him that choſeth hyr,</l>
                  <l>For I wold not haue the, therin to be begylde,</l>
                  <l>As I was once nere, when I was younge and wylde,</l>
                  <l>Which if it were not, for lacke of time, and ſpace,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhouldeſt plainelis heare, my ſolly in this caſe,</l>
                  <l>I pray you (quod I) take the paines to declare it,</l>
                  <l>And for lacke of time, and ſpace, do not ſpare it,</l>
                  <l>Nay not ſo (quod he) for we are now, nere the to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fermers plare</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:13"/>
                  <l>Whith whome I entende, to comon a litell ſpace,</l>
                  <l>Touchinge, my buſyneſſe, wherfore I hether came,</l>
                  <l>Which beinge once finiſhed, yf thou wilt thane,</l>
                  <l>Beare me companie, homward, in the waye,</l>
                  <l>I wil declare, al the reſt, I haue yet to ſaye,</l>
                  <l>To the which, I aunſwered, that I wold veary galdlye</l>
                  <l>So that he wolde, diſpacth his matters quyckelie.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Here endeth the firſt parte.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <lg>
                  <l>ANone, we ſpyed, the fermour, at his gate ſtandinge,</l>
                  <l>Who as ſoone, as he, perceaued vs comminge,</l>
                  <l>Gentillie, ſaluted vs, callinge hym by hys name,</l>
                  <l>And we did likewiſe gretchi, with chanckes for the ſame,</l>
                  <l>With whome this aged man, hauinge a while walked,</l>
                  <l>And concerning his errande, hao with him fully talked,</l>
                  <l>The fermour had vs in, where we had good cheare</l>
                  <l>And taryed the mountenance, of halfe an boure,</l>
                  <l>Then toke we our leaue, of the fermere,</l>
                  <l>And ſo ſtreight wayes departed, from him there,</l>
                  <l>And when we were homewarde, a prettie waye,</l>
                  <l>To the ſaide olde man, I began thus to ſaye,</l>
                  <l>Nowe Sire, and it pleaſe you, in your tale to procede,</l>
                  <l>I am moch deſirous, to here thende in dede,</l>
                  <l>Well ſaid, ſonne (quod he) then giue diligente care,</l>
                  <l>When I was of thage, of two and twentie yeare,</l>
                  <l>Veary luſtie I was, and pleaſaunte withall,</l>
                  <l>To ſinge, daunce, and playe at the ball,</l>
                  <l>To runne, to wraſtle, to caſte the axeltre or barre,</l>
                  <l>Either with hande, or foote, I coulde caſte it as farre,</l>
                  <l>And all other feates, as nunblie doo,</l>
                  <l>As any in the towne, Idwelled in thoo</l>
                  <l>Fyne, feate, neate, proper and ſmall,</l>
                  <l>I was then, though I ſaye it, and faire withall,</l>
                  <l>Yt appeareth no leſſe (quod I) for you beare your age ſeare,</l>
                  <l>Well, let paſſe (quod he) ſuche then was my cheare,</l>
                  <l>And beſides all this, I coulde then fynelie playe,</l>
                  <l>On the harpe, mothe better, then nowe farre a waye,</l>
                  <l>By which my minſtrelſie, and my faire ſpeache, and ſporte,</l>
                  <l>All the maydes in the paryſhe, to me did reaſorte,</l>
                  <l>Eche loued, luſtie Lewes, for ſo they me named,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:14"/>
                  <l>Not one of them all, my companie refrayned,</l>
                  <l>Paryſhe clercke I was then, of the towne there,</l>
                  <l>To helpe the prieſt to maſſe, and ſing in the quere,</l>
                  <l>With ſuche liuinge as I had, I lyued withoute care,</l>
                  <l>Wyfe nor child had I none, for whome I ſhould ſpare,</l>
                  <l>A neighbour ther was, a veary honeſt man,</l>
                  <l>Dwellinge within the ſame, our pariſh than,</l>
                  <l>Which a daughter had that in bewtie did excell,</l>
                  <l>And as then me thoughte, aboue all other bare the bell,</l>
                  <l>Of meane ſtature ſhe was, and therto well made,</l>
                  <l>Chearefull in contenaunce, and a good fauour hade,</l>
                  <l>A ſmilinge ſmoth loke, with a wanton Eye.</l>
                  <l>She was the amiableſt dameſell, that euer I did ſet,</l>
                  <l>A fine congue ſhe alſo had, and hir woordes could well plate,</l>
                  <l>And in hir communicacion, a veary ſinguler grace,</l>
                  <l>Modeſte, demure, and ſadde ſhe appeared,</l>
                  <l>And neuer theleſſe famylier, ynoughe, as the tyme required,</l>
                  <l>In hir apparrell trymme, which was euer more white,</l>
                  <l>To haue ſeen hir on the holye daye, was a goodlie ſighte,</l>
                  <l>So womanlie was hir pace, in hir geſture to and froo,</l>
                  <l>Upright as a bolte, and lyke one fleinge did ſhe goo,</l>
                  <l>This maide was come home, but late from the citie,</l>
                  <l>Where ſhe had ſerued, yeares two or thre,</l>
                  <l>The firſt tyme I ſawe hir, was on a holy daye at noone,</l>
                  <l>Goinge home ward fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the church, when ſeruice was doone,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe wanton, well fauoured fairnes, ſo caught me,</l>
                  <l>That earneſtlye to loue hir, lightlye ſhe brought me,</l>
                  <l>By whom, I was then ſtrycken, with ſuch a veament pange,</l>
                  <l>That the holie water bucket, from me ſtraight I flange,</l>
                  <l>And great haſte I made, ronning ſwiftlye after,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe I wolde, ſo gladlie ouertake hir,</l>
                  <l>At laſt I ouertooke hir, but with moth a doo,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhe me ſaluted, and I hir alſo,</l>
                  <l>Hir ſiſter went with hir, who bad me welcome,</l>
                  <l>Sayinge, whether in ſuche haſte, good Lewes, do you rone.</l>
                  <l>In fayth (quod I) ſince you deſyre, to knowe,</l>
                  <l>To a neighbours houſe, who dwelleth here by lowe,</l>
                  <l>The haſte that I made, was for your companie,</l>
                  <l>And to knowe what faire mayde, this is truelie,</l>
                  <l>Mary (quod ſhe) ſhe is none other,</l>
                  <l>But myne owne ſiſter borne of father and mother,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:14"/>
                  <l>And ſiſter Grace (quod ſhe) I pray you, of him acquainta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce take,</l>
                  <l>For with his melodie, he doth vs often, mery make,</l>
                  <l>I tell you Grace (quod ſhe) he is an honeſt man,</l>
                  <l>And on his minion harpe, full well playe he can,</l>
                  <l>To the which, this Grace, aunſwered, veary ſadlye,</l>
                  <l>And I wold be acquainted, with him veary gladlye,</l>
                  <l>And this paſſed furth, they were nere at home,</l>
                  <l>So then takinge my leaue, I parted them frome,</l>
                  <l>And this, was the firſt time, of our gretinge,</l>
                  <l>Which was to me, anvnhappie metinge,</l>
                  <l>As ye ſhall plainlie, here after well perceaue.</l>
                  <l>Before the crueltie, of cruell Cupido, did me leaue,</l>
                  <l>Backwarde I went, where my dinner was dighte,</l>
                  <l>And ſtill by the waye, my harte full fore ſighere,</l>
                  <l>When home I was come, to dinner I was ſette,</l>
                  <l>My hert was full heauie, no meate coulde I eate,</l>
                  <l>After dynner downe, on my bed I dyd lie,</l>
                  <l>Moch muſing with my ſelfe, what thinge it might bee,</l>
                  <l>That ſo ſoudanlie had ſtricken, my harte with ſoch woo,</l>
                  <l>And ſo ſoone had driuen, my mirth, and pleaſure, me froo,</l>
                  <l>No wayr, could my witte, by wiſdome deuyſe,</l>
                  <l>Howe this ſadneſſe, and thought, on me ſhould aryſe,</l>
                  <l>Except it weare, by beholding the maide,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe bewtie, and fauour, was euer in my heade,</l>
                  <l>To haue ſlept faine I wold, but it wold not bee,</l>
                  <l>Yet at the laſt, a ſhorte ſlomber tooke mee,</l>
                  <l>In which ſlomber, alſo my thought I dyd ſee,</l>
                  <l>The dameſell, whoſe fayreneſſe, before ſo perced mee</l>
                  <l>Euenſong tyme came, vp then did I ryſe,</l>
                  <l>And went to the church, to heare the ſeruſte,</l>
                  <l>My loue, to euenſong came not, as I thought that ſhe wolde,</l>
                  <l>Therfore was I ſorie, my harte was full colde,</l>
                  <l>At ſupper, no thinge could I eate, then thought I beſte,</l>
                  <l>In time conuenient, to hye me to my neſte,</l>
                  <l>No reſt could I take, my ſlepe was cleane gone,</l>
                  <l>My harte was full heauie, and colde as a ſtone,</l>
                  <l>The morning then came, when gone was the night,</l>
                  <l>The ayre was cleare, the ſunne ſhyned bryghte,</l>
                  <l>Abrode I then walcked, the birdes for to heare,</l>
                  <l>Where a frende of myne, met me and ared, what cheare,</l>
                  <l>Trulye (quod I) I am nowe excedinge faints</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:15"/>
                  <l>Yet knowe I not the cauſe, which my harte doth ſo taynte,</l>
                  <l>God a mend you (quod he) and ſo went his waye,</l>
                  <l>This in miſerable caſe, I paſſed that daye,</l>
                  <l>And many a daye more, till ſheringe tyme came,</l>
                  <l>Hir father ſhearinge ſhepe, to his feaſte had me thane,</l>
                  <l>Glade was Lewes, tho, thinckinge then ſhall I ſpeake,</l>
                  <l>At leaſure, with my loue, and my minde, to hyr breake,</l>
                  <l>Than ſhall ſhe knowe, the wo, and the ſmarte,</l>
                  <l>The heaueneſſe, and ſorowe, of my woful harte,</l>
                  <l>The reſties mghtes, and vnquiet dayes,</l>
                  <l>The heauie thoughtes, which troublith me alwaies,</l>
                  <l>I will alſo then, yf that Idare,</l>
                  <l>The botome, of my minde, to hir declare,</l>
                  <l>Then ſaid I ſofcely to my ſelfe, God lende me,</l>
                  <l>A conuemente tyme, and that he wil ſende me,</l>
                  <l>To obtaine at hir handes, ſuche fauour and grace,</l>
                  <l>That my humble requeſte, maye be heard, and take place,</l>
                  <l>What nede lenger proceſſe, the ſhepe ſhearinge daye,</l>
                  <l>That I ſo longe loked for, at laſt came I ſaie,</l>
                  <l>To hir fathers houſe I came, as they were at dyner,</l>
                  <l>Hee had me hartelie welcome, and in the beſt maner,</l>
                  <l>To the table was I ſette, downe on the benche,</l>
                  <l>Where I might ſede, ful in me eyes, on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> welfauored we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che,</l>
                  <l>Who there ſerued the table, as then was the gyſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſurelie ſhe wayted in mooſt wom anlie wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Whiche ſhe wel could do, for as I ſaid before,</l>
                  <l>In the cytic had ſhe bene, of good maner to learne ſtore.</l>
                  <l>Littell meate could I eate, which was noted well than,</l>
                  <l>By the maydes mother, and alſo by hir good man,</l>
                  <l>What cheare good Lewes, tell me ſhe ſaide,</l>
                  <l>Ye looke veary ſadlie, as one halfe diſmaide,</l>
                  <l>What man quod ſhe, where is your mirth become,</l>
                  <l>Me thinckes ye muſe, on the man in the mone,</l>
                  <l>Be mery I praye you, and therwith ſhe me kerued.</l>
                  <l>But my harte was hollie, on the maide that ſerued,</l>
                  <l>And afterward, when dyner was done</l>
                  <l>And the geaſtes departing, awaye euerich one,</l>
                  <l>I alſo hauinge rendered theim, thanckes for my cheare,</l>
                  <l>Went homeward, with the companie, that were going there,</l>
                  <l>Beinge both of my purpoſe, that I came for vnſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de,</l>
                  <l>And alſo wourfe at eaſe, both in my hert and heauie heade,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:15"/>
                  <l>Then, inſtamed was my lout, and grewe more and more,</l>
                  <l>Whiche was but a litel, kendeled before,</l>
                  <l>The maladye, which before, might in tyme, haue ben healed,</l>
                  <l>Wared nowe incurable, and that well I fealed,</l>
                  <l>My harpe, which was wonte, ſo ſwetelie to ſounde,</l>
                  <l>Lay nowe vntouched, for me on the grounde,</l>
                  <l>My breaſt, which before, many ſolkes, did reioſce,</l>
                  <l>Began cleane to tourue, and horſe waxed my voice,</l>
                  <l>My collour, which in tymes paſt, ſo lyuelie did apeare,</l>
                  <l>Was vaded awaye, and chaunged his cheare,</l>
                  <l>My legges, whiche were ſometyme, nymble to daunce,</l>
                  <l>Was ſhronken cleane, by this vnhappye chaunce,</l>
                  <l>I was neare a conſumpcion, all ſtrength was gon,</l>
                  <l>So hollye was I altered, that I was ſcace knowen,</l>
                  <l>At laſt I conſydered, the beſt waye to procede,</l>
                  <l>If I thoughte, by her helpe, to be cured in dede,</l>
                  <l>Was, that ſhe ſyrſte, vnderſtande ſhoulde,</l>
                  <l>My woe, and dyſtreſſe, and then yf ſhe woulde,</l>
                  <l>Of pytye, and clemencye, relieue my great payne,</l>
                  <l>This waye, to be the beſt, I thought ſure, and playne,</l>
                  <l>For Phiſirions, do not vſe, to miniſter remedy,</l>
                  <l>Before, they are inſtructed, in their pacientes maladye,</l>
                  <l>So it fell, in a mornynge not longe after,</l>
                  <l>That I chaunfed, to walke, throughe the common paffure,</l>
                  <l>Where the milche kyne, of the towne, the daye tyme dyd fede,</l>
                  <l>And all the maydens, in the paryſhe, did mylke in that ſtede,</l>
                  <l>Emongeſt whome, Graces ſiſter, was one there,</l>
                  <l>And therefore, I mynded, to banyſhe all feare,</l>
                  <l>And ſo to make open, and breake hollie to her,</l>
                  <l>The full care, and effecte, of all this hole mattier,</l>
                  <l>But fyrſte, certayne wordes, a farre of to proue hir,</l>
                  <l>I would caſte out, to ſee, how this care, would moue hir,</l>
                  <l>And howe ſhe would take it, ere I meant to declare,</l>
                  <l>And vpon the lykynge, of hir aunſwere, not for to ſpare,</l>
                  <l>Thus drawynge nere, I had hir good morowe,</l>
                  <l>What gentyl Lewes (quod ſhe) God kepe you from ſorowe,</l>
                  <l>Howe do you, what wynde dryue you hether,</l>
                  <l>This mornynge ſo earlye, and I praye you whether,</l>
                  <l>Are ye thus walkynge, youre ſelfe all alone,</l>
                  <l>I thincke ſuerlye, ye haue ſome pretye one,</l>
                  <l>That cauſeth you, daylye, to this place to come,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:16"/>
                  <l>Well wanton, well, thoughe not all, yet I knowe ſome,</l>
                  <l>Loſen Iohan (quod I) for ſo was hir name,</l>
                  <l>In iudgynge amyſſe, ye are greatly to blame,</l>
                  <l>For yf I for loue, reaſorte, to any in this place,</l>
                  <l>It is trulye, to you, or to your ſyſter Grace,</l>
                  <l>For ſurely, you two, of bewtie beare the floure,</l>
                  <l>This iudgement, muſt I geue, though I dye, w<hi rend="sup">e</hi>in an houre,</l>
                  <l>No Lewes (quod ſhe) then ye iudge not well,</l>
                  <l>For there be maydes, a great many that vs do excell,</l>
                  <l>Yet for the gentylnes, I haue alwayes ſent,</l>
                  <l>And the honeſt behauioure, that continually hath bene,</l>
                  <l>In you heretofore, I thincke you worthy to obtayne,</l>
                  <l>As good, and as fayre, as any in this paryſhe dothe remayne,</l>
                  <l>Yea, and thoughe ſhe were, myne owne dere ſyſter,</l>
                  <l>I woulde thincke hir, well beſtowed, yf ye had her,</l>
                  <l>I thancke you fayre Iohn (quod I) that it dothe you pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Vnworthely, me ſo louynglye to prayſe,</l>
                  <l>And yf God my lyfe, any whyle wyll preſerue,</l>
                  <l>Youre gentle kyndenes, I truſt to deſerue,</l>
                  <l>And therwith, as it were muſynge, a prety whyle I ſtayed,</l>
                  <l>What Lewes (quod ſhe) me thinkes ye are as one dyſmaied,</l>
                  <l>Wheron ſo ſtudy you, a peny for your thoughte,</l>
                  <l>In faythe quod I, if ye knew it, yet were it worth naught,</l>
                  <l>My thinckes quod ſhe, ye are chaunged in euery race,</l>
                  <l>What, hath any mayde, rauyſhed your hart, from his place,</l>
                  <l>Tel me (ſhe ſayd) and my beſt counſayle ye ſhall haue,</l>
                  <l>With all that I can do as God my ſoule ſaue,</l>
                  <l>Oh (quod I) my harte is wrapte full of woe,</l>
                  <l>Yet haue I no faythfull frende, it to ſhowe,</l>
                  <l>I ſhal tel you Lewes (quod ſhe) what ſo euer ye ſaye,</l>
                  <l>To me, thincke it ſure, vnder locke, and kaye,</l>
                  <l>For euer herynge it, by me ſpoken agayne,</l>
                  <l>Ercepte the ſame be, for your profyte playne,</l>
                  <l>Well, ſince ye wyl nedes know quod I my careful myſerye,</l>
                  <l>Ye ſhall heare the ſame, in fewe wordes playnlye,</l>
                  <l>So it is, that, that ſayre ſwere bloſſome, your ſyſter Grace,</l>
                  <l>Hath holly, my loue, and harte, in ſuche cace,</l>
                  <l>That neyther wandrynge, nor walkinge, whether ſo euer I go,</l>
                  <l>Neyther playinge, nor workynge, what ſo euer I do,</l>
                  <l>Neyther wakynge, nor watchynge, any tyme, or ſpace,</l>
                  <l>Neyther reſtynge, nor ſlepynge, in any maner place,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:16"/>
                  <l>But at all tymes, and euermore continuallye,</l>
                  <l>Hir amiable countenaunce, reſtreth in my mynde daylye,</l>
                  <l>No pleaſure, me pleaſeth, my mirth is amated,</l>
                  <l>No ioyes, my delyte, my lyfelyneſſe is abated,</l>
                  <l>No muſycke, me reioyſeth, theyr ſoundes, are vnſwete,</l>
                  <l>No paſtymes, I paſſe on, as at this tyme vnmete,</l>
                  <l>No worke, is well wrought, now vnder my handes,</l>
                  <l>Nor I am nothing, as I was, before I entered loues bades,</l>
                  <l>So that I well knowe, I am lyke to ſuſtayne,</l>
                  <l>Deathes darte, very ſhortely, if I do not obtayne,</l>
                  <l>The rather, hir loue who now hath the meaſure,</l>
                  <l>Me to ſlaye or reuyue euen at hir owne pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>Whiche I would ſhe dyd ſhortly for the eaſe of my payne,</l>
                  <l>By the darte of cruel deathe deuorynge me cleane,</l>
                  <l>Nowe haue ye hearde all quod I, and more as I ſaye,</l>
                  <l>Then euer to any other I tolde before this daye,</l>
                  <l>Wherin I ſhal deſyre you to playe an honeſt parte,</l>
                  <l>For the ſpedy quietynge of my poore wretched harte,</l>
                  <l>Marie (quod Iohan) now I perceaue very well,</l>
                  <l>Of your ſadnes, and ſorowe, there is no meruel,</l>
                  <l>That hath ſuch an Impoſtome bredynge in your breſt,</l>
                  <l>Which worketh you wourthely full waywarde reſte,</l>
                  <l>No wonder it is though ye loke wan and pale,</l>
                  <l>For loue hath made you drincke a draught of ſower ale,</l>
                  <l>I toke you neuer ſo tender, ſo ſoone to be caughte,</l>
                  <l>With the louely linckes of loue which are ſo quickly wrought,</l>
                  <l>Ye were wont before this tyme alwayes to ſaye,</l>
                  <l>That they were very fooles that to loue did obaye,</l>
                  <l>And that it was impoſſible any wyſe man to be,</l>
                  <l>So earneſtly ſet in loue in any degree,</l>
                  <l>But that when he would alwaies, well he myghte,</l>
                  <l>Full eaſelye put the ſame out of his heade quite,</l>
                  <l>But now ye are caught in the ſame nette,</l>
                  <l>Which in tymes paſt ye greatly did neglecte,</l>
                  <l>When ye ſawe any louer, ye laughed him to ſcorne,</l>
                  <l>But loue hath now brought you to ſcole to learne,</l>
                  <l>And ſuerly quod ſhe, to deme in myne entent,</l>
                  <l>Ye haue worthely of loue deſerued this punyſhment,</l>
                  <l>Welquod I, to a man that is falen in myſery and woo,</l>
                  <l>Good comforte behoueth, and not chidynge ſoo,</l>
                  <l>My faulte I confcſſe, what nedeth more,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:17"/>
                  <l>I deſyre youre good counſayle for curynge of my ſore,</l>
                  <l>Whiche waye I maye beſt by youre good aduyſe,</l>
                  <l>Atcheue this ſo doubtefull and daungerouſe an enterprpſe,</l>
                  <l>Well Lewes (quod Iohan) nowe that I knoo,</l>
                  <l>What woman ſhe is that worketh you this woo,</l>
                  <l>Let me alone, I wyll fyrſte moue this mattier,</l>
                  <l>Sone at nyght in bed, I wyll earneſtly at hir,</l>
                  <l>As ye ſhall perceaue here by this tyme to morowe,</l>
                  <l>Other eaſe or increaſe of all youre hole ſorowe,</l>
                  <l>Therefore in the meane tyme, be of good cheare,</l>
                  <l>And I wyll dilygently worke in youre cauſe I ſweare,</l>
                  <l>Whereof I thanked her, ſayinge gladlye I woulde,</l>
                  <l>Hir gentylnes conſyder, yf euer I coulde,</l>
                  <l>And hauynge once kiſt hir, I toke my leaue thane,</l>
                  <l>This departinge from hir, whome warde I came,</l>
                  <l>The morowe nerte after, I came eſteſones to the ſame place,</l>
                  <l>To heare yf I were lyke to obtaine any grace,</l>
                  <l>Iohan was not then come, I ſtayed a lytle whyle,</l>
                  <l>At laſt not farre thence I ſawe hir commynge ouer a ſtyle,</l>
                  <l>With hir pail in hir hande, then I went hir to mete,</l>
                  <l>And gentyllie ſaluted hir, ſhe did lyke wyſe me grete,</l>
                  <l>Eyther death and double ſorow (quod I Iohan) do you brynge,</l>
                  <l>Or lyfe to reuyue me whiche am nowe dyinge,</l>
                  <l>Neyther of them bothe (quod ſhe) but hope haue I broughte,</l>
                  <l>Thereby partely to fede and relieue youre heaupe thoughte,</l>
                  <l>Then ſaye on (quod I) and nomore tyme waſte,</l>
                  <l>That happy hope to heare I gladly make haſte,</l>
                  <l>Peſter nyghte beynge bothe (quod ſhe) in oure bed layed,</l>
                  <l>I tourned me towardes my ſyſter, and euen thus I ſayde,</l>
                  <l>Oh Iohan (quod I) I then wyſhed me in youre place,</l>
                  <l>To haue declared my ſelfe to hir my hole cace,</l>
                  <l>Youre wyſhe was but voyde (quod ſhe) but harke what I tell,</l>
                  <l>I ared Grace how ſhe dyd, and ſhe ſayde very well,</l>
                  <l>Howe ſo euer you do (quod I) lye nowe at youre caſe,</l>
                  <l>I knowe other ſome are as yll at eaſe,</l>
                  <l>Whiche for you and for youre ſake to be playne,</l>
                  <l>Muche myſery, myſchiefe and care do ſuſtayne,</l>
                  <l>Whiche greueth me muthe, for ſynce the worlde began,</l>
                  <l>God neuer created a more honeſter man,</l>
                  <l>And he is lyke for youre loue as far as I can geſſe,</l>
                  <l>Shortely to dye, ſuche is hys deadlye diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:17"/>
                  <l>For my loue (ſyſter Iohan) quod Grace to me then,</l>
                  <l>In this paryſhe I am as yet knowen of very fewe men,</l>
                  <l>And fewer do I knowe, then howe maye it be,</l>
                  <l>That any man is vered ſo for loue of me,</l>
                  <l>Who is it I praye you, once name hym to me,</l>
                  <l>And then yf I knowe hym, I wyll tell you quod ſhe,</l>
                  <l>Nay ſyſter Grace (quod I) that ſhal not be,</l>
                  <l>Before ſyrſte ſome promyſe ye make vnto me,</l>
                  <l>That ye ſhall not at the fyrſte kyll his harte cleane,</l>
                  <l>By geuyuge hym a naye, or by any other meane,</l>
                  <l>Of vnkyndenes on youre behalfe, but ye ſhall yf ye can,</l>
                  <l>Braunte hym youre loue, before an other man,</l>
                  <l>For I wyll aſſure you yf ye perfertly knewe,</l>
                  <l>His good gentle behauioure bothe honeſt and true,</l>
                  <l>Whiche is ſo pleaſaunte a parſon to ſynge and to daunce,</l>
                  <l>And is ſkylled in inſtrumentes for youre paſtaunce,</l>
                  <l>So well can ſhote, wreſtel, and leape ſo lyghte,</l>
                  <l>So handeſome a man in euery mans ſyghte,</l>
                  <l>And beſydes this more ſorowe hath ſuſtayned,</l>
                  <l>For youre ſake, and is alſo ſo cruelly payned,</l>
                  <l>That deathe to hym were a greate deale ſweater,</l>
                  <l>Then to lyue as he doth he thynketh it muche better,</l>
                  <l>And yf in youre defaulte ye ſhoulde ſuffer hym to dye,</l>
                  <l>For lacke of youre loue what proſyte therby,</l>
                  <l>Shoulde ye receaue, nay rather yt myght name you,</l>
                  <l>A murderer I ſaye whiche would greately ſhame you,</l>
                  <l>And whome ſhould ye kyll no enemy pardye,</l>
                  <l>But a mooſt true louer who loueth you hartelye,</l>
                  <l>Well (quod my ſyſter) to loue hym ye ſhall pardon me,</l>
                  <l>For I wyll do nothynge in that matter trulye,</l>
                  <l>But this promyſe to graunte to you I am contente,</l>
                  <l>At the fyrſte tyme no naye he ſhall haue I concente,</l>
                  <l>Therefore tell me hys name wythout any delaye,</l>
                  <l>And then ye ſhall heare what I wyll further ſaye,</l>
                  <l>It is (quod I) Lewes the cleare he of the townr,</l>
                  <l>Who for youre ſake in myſery is toſſed vp and downe,</l>
                  <l>Why ſyſter Iohan than ſayde ſhe vnto me,</l>
                  <l>I thoughte ye would not of all other ſucrlye,</l>
                  <l>Haue moued me to this lyghtnes I ſaye,</l>
                  <l>But rather haue perſwaded me if I had bene bent that waye,</l>
                  <l>Why Brace (quod I) I meane no diſhone ſtye,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:18"/>
                  <l>For he would haue you to be hys wyfe very gladlye,</l>
                  <l>So muche the more quod ſhe, it is to be borne,</l>
                  <l>But I tell you nowe as I tolde you beforne,</l>
                  <l>I wyl as yet, neyther loue hym, nor any other,</l>
                  <l>By other perſwation of ſyſter or brother,</l>
                  <l>Alſo ye might wel thincke, me very haſty ſyſter Iohan,</l>
                  <l>If I ſhould be a louer ſo ſoone as I came home,</l>
                  <l>And yf he loued me ſo earneſtly as ye haue tolde,</l>
                  <l>To haue moued me him ſelfe before this tyme he would,</l>
                  <l>But he thought of his deſyre hym ſelfe to be ſure,</l>
                  <l>When you to be his broker he fyrſte dyd procure,</l>
                  <l>And very late it is quod ſhe, therfore fall to your reſt,</l>
                  <l>And herewith medle no more in earneſt or ieſt,</l>
                  <l>Not one worde more quod Iohan, of hir get coulde I,</l>
                  <l>For to ſlepe ſhe gaue hir where ſhe ſlept by and by,</l>
                  <l>And thus haue I (Lewes) for you broken the mattier,</l>
                  <l>It behoueth your ſelfe next to attempte her,</l>
                  <l>And ſpare not to ſpeake, yf ye mynde for to ſpede,</l>
                  <l>Who truſteth to obtayne, muſt put away orede,</l>
                  <l>But ſuerly (Tewes) ſynce ſhe now knoweth that ſhe loued is,</l>
                  <l>She is not therof a lytle proude I wyſſe,</l>
                  <l>Alaſſe ſayde I then, I would I were ded,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhould be at eaſe, bothe my hart, and myne hed,</l>
                  <l>Vnlucky fortune I may it call,</l>
                  <l>Which forceth me to loue one amongeſt all,</l>
                  <l>Who neyther regardeth my woofull dyſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Neyther wyll coumforte me by any word of kyndneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Well quod Iohan, it may be that ſhe wyll heare,</l>
                  <l>Your ſelfe muche better then me a meſſengere,</l>
                  <l>And hether to morowe ſhal ſhe come to mylke in my ſtede,</l>
                  <l>For I muſt taly at home to brue and bake brede,</l>
                  <l>And to ſpeake to hir then ye nede not my counſayle,</l>
                  <l>For ye are wyſe ynoughe to tell your owne tale,</l>
                  <l>And in the meane whyle ye ſhalbe ſure,</l>
                  <l>I wyll do my beſt your way to procure,</l>
                  <l>Thus parted we then withcut wordes any moo,</l>
                  <l>I to the churche, and ſhe homewarde dyd goo,</l>
                  <l>The next mornynge came which I thought very lenge,</l>
                  <l>And no meruayle, for my payne was ſo ſtronge,</l>
                  <l>Then to the common yaſture I tymely me hyed.</l>
                  <l>Where my onely hartes luſte on mylkynge I ſpyed,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:18"/>
                  <l>I mended my pace, and at the laſte to hir came,</l>
                  <l>I had her good morowe, ſhe ſaid welcome yonge man,</l>
                  <l>Howe do you ſaid I, myne owne ſwete harte,</l>
                  <l>Your loue hath cauſed me with much ſorow to ſmarte,</l>
                  <l>So depely is engraued in me the bewty of your face,</l>
                  <l>Your pleaſaunt tonge, &amp; behauiour myne owne loue Grace,</l>
                  <l>The ſeature, the properneſſe of youre body fyne,</l>
                  <l>And your louely countenance hath ſo perced myne yen,</l>
                  <l>That I am hollye yours, hellye in euery condicion,</l>
                  <l>To loue you, and ſerue you, with humble ſubmiſſion,</l>
                  <l>Abydynge your pleaſure, and wyll to ſuſtayne,</l>
                  <l>So longe as lyfe within me ſhall remayne,</l>
                  <l>In conſyderacion wherof I deſyre to obtayne,</l>
                  <l>Nothynge but good loue, for true loue agayne,</l>
                  <l>Younge man quod ſhe, I am ſory of your woo,</l>
                  <l>And muche more ſorye that ye ſet youre mynde ſo,</l>
                  <l>As to me to beare ſuch loue, and good wyll,</l>
                  <l>Wherin I feare your tyme ye ſhall ſpyll,</l>
                  <l>In hopynge for a thynge ye cannot obtayne,</l>
                  <l>Which at length wil brynge to you double payne,</l>
                  <l>And as for me I meane not yet to marye,</l>
                  <l>I am younge ynoughe, I thancke God I can tarye,</l>
                  <l>And alſo I wyl, for ought I yet knowe,</l>
                  <l>Yeres two or three truly to ſhewe,</l>
                  <l>Neyther would I, ye ſhould thincke I do not eſteme you,</l>
                  <l>For truly to iudge I can none otherwyſe deme you,</l>
                  <l>But for youre behauioure, qualities, and honeſtye,</l>
                  <l>Ye are worthy to haue one muche better then I,</l>
                  <l>Oh bewtyfull Grace (quod I) yf Grace wyll ſhewe any grace,</l>
                  <l>I pray you that it may appeare in this my heauy cace,</l>
                  <l>And not to confounde me wyth ſuche a cruel naye,</l>
                  <l>Neyther ſo mercyles with your wordes me vtterly to ſlaye,</l>
                  <l>And ſuffer not thus pitie, and mercy to be banyſhed,</l>
                  <l>From a creature ſo fayre by God, formed, and faſhioned,</l>
                  <l>Neyther denye not your name, in any tyine or place,</l>
                  <l>But accordynge to your name, ſhewe me ſome grace,</l>
                  <l>Sir (ſayde ſhe) what nede longer proceſſe to make,</l>
                  <l>There ſemeth in you follye, ſuche heuyneſſe to take,</l>
                  <l>For me that am not nowe to mary dyſpoſed,</l>
                  <l>Neyther to whome before this tyme your loue ye dyſcloſed,</l>
                  <l>In dede to you I tolde it not (ſaid I) but your ſyſter I meued,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:19"/>
                  <l>Wyſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e wylleth men to go where they may beſt be relieued,</l>
                  <l>I durſt not before (quod I) not knowynge how ye would take it,</l>
                  <l>Truly (quod the) eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as I do now I would haue cleane forſake it,</l>
                  <l>And Lewes this follye to leaue I could wyſhe you ſtyll,</l>
                  <l>By wyſedome to be ruled and flee from your wyll,</l>
                  <l>Fynallye I deſyre you to take it for the beſt,</l>
                  <l>That I here not your ſute, nor graunte your requeſt,</l>
                  <l>Oh Grace (quod I) ſince it is your pleaſure to ſpyſme,</l>
                  <l>I ſhal abyde youre mercy to ſaue me or kyll me,</l>
                  <l>Youre harde harted harte I praye God once to mollefye,</l>
                  <l>Some compaſſion to graunte me before that I die,</l>
                  <l>And thus God be with you my loue mooſt vnkynde,</l>
                  <l>Fare well gentle Lewes (quod ſhe) God alter your mynde,</l>
                  <l>And ſende you to put away this ſanry quietlye,</l>
                  <l>Whiche hath brought you in this wofull myſerye,</l>
                  <l>Thus away went I then halfe in diſpayre,</l>
                  <l>My hearte greatly vexed betwene hope and feare,</l>
                  <l>Within two dayes after I met with hir ſyſter Iohan,</l>
                  <l>To whome I ſhewed and made my heauy mone,</l>
                  <l>Declarynge to hir al the wordes that were,</l>
                  <l>Betwene me and my loue Grace hir ſyſter,</l>
                  <l>Well quod Iohan I wyſhe that this next nyghte,</l>
                  <l>With your harpe ye holde your waye to oure houſe right,</l>
                  <l>And there vnderneth our chamber wyndowe,</l>
                  <l>In ſyngynge and playinge let hir heare what ye can do,</l>
                  <l>Your melodie may cauſe her ſtobbourne harde harte,</l>
                  <l>To loue you parchaunce, it maye hir ſo conuerte,</l>
                  <l>And this maye ye eaſelye doo withoute any ylle,</l>
                  <l>For of bothe oure parentes ye haue the good wyll,</l>
                  <l>And thus geuynge Iohan thankes for hir counſayle ſo good,</l>
                  <l>Home warde I hyed me, in haſte by the roode,</l>
                  <l>My harpe for to tune, and ſome ditie to make,</l>
                  <l>The whiche I myghte ſynge and playe for hir ſake,</l>
                  <l>The night at laſte came, and when the clocke had runne nyne,</l>
                  <l>Thether I went with my harpe as I thought it was tyme,</l>
                  <l>For as theſomer ſeaſon required twilight it was thane,</l>
                  <l>When to hir fathers houſe that I came,</l>
                  <l>A bedde were they all, no ſturrvnge herde I,</l>
                  <l>My harpe oute of his cace I pluckt by and by,</l>
                  <l>And ſtrake vp ſuddenly a very pretye rounde,</l>
                  <l>Whiche my harpe then newe ſtringed meryllye dyd ſo unde,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:19"/>
                  <l>Another daunce or two, I then alſo played,</l>
                  <l>Whiche beynge once fynyſhed, I ſodenly ſtayed,</l>
                  <l>And this ballet hereaſter I began for to ſynge,</l>
                  <l>My harpe hare the note, which merely did rynge,</l>
               </lg>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh my loue Grace,</l>
                     <l>Youre bewtyfull face,</l>
                     <l>Hathe perced ſo my breff,</l>
                     <l>Youre countenaunce mylde,</l>
                     <l>With youre tonge ſo wel fylde,</l>
                     <l>Is cauſer of all myne vnreſt,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not Troylus of Troye,</l>
                     <l>By Creſſide hysioye,</l>
                     <l>In loue was euer ſo ſet on ſyre,</l>
                     <l>Neyther Piramus the younge,</l>
                     <l>By the loue of Thiſby ſo ſtronge</l>
                     <l>Or burnte in ſuche hote deſyre,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Neyther Hercules the myghtye,</l>
                     <l>By Dianiras bewtye,</l>
                     <l>Was at any tyme ſo ouercome,</l>
                     <l>Neyther Sampſon the ſtronge,</l>
                     <l>With loue was ſo wronge,</l>
                     <l>Of Dallida the wicked woman</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Neyther that wofull Dido,</l>
                     <l>Eneas loued ſo,</l>
                     <l>As I do nowe loue you hartely.</l>
                     <l>For in good faythe,</l>
                     <l>Yt wyll be my deathe,</l>
                     <l>Excepte yt extende your mercy,</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <lg>
                  <l>And when this ballet was fully ended,</l>
                  <l>My comforte was neuer the more amended</l>
                  <l>For no aunſwere at all would ſhe to me ſaye,</l>
                  <l>Yet without any whit playinge a while did I ſtaye,</l>
                  <l>At laſt hir father bad me good nyghte,</l>
                  <l>So did hir mother and hir ſyſter full ryghte,</l>
                  <l>And gaue my harty thankes for that my payne,</l>
                  <l>But no farewel of Grace coulde I obtayne,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:20"/>
                  <l>Then home ſtrayghte I wente full ſadlye agayne,</l>
                  <l>Where I languiſhed all that nyghte, in terrphle payne,</l>
                  <l>And thus continued by the ſpace of a moneth,</l>
                  <l>And then one of oure neyghbours to me ſtraighte commeth,</l>
                  <l>And of hys owne good wyll vnmoued there,</l>
                  <l>Offered to me his onely daughter and heire,</l>
                  <l>Whiche in good lande after hym ſhoulde ſpende,</l>
                  <l>Fyue markes by the yere vntyl hir lyues ende,</l>
                  <l>And the dameſell was alſo indifferente fayre,</l>
                  <l>And ſure a good huſwyfe as after dyd appeare,</l>
                  <l>After thankes for hys good wyll, I then to hym ſayde,</l>
                  <l>My mynde he ſhoulde knowe vpon the ſyghte of the mayde,</l>
                  <l>What wyll ye more, ſhe lyked me well,</l>
                  <l>And was contented to take me wherby it fell,</l>
                  <l>That ſhortely after maryed we were,</l>
                  <l>And haue louyngely lyued hitherto together,</l>
                  <l>And haue nere runne oute oure courſe as ye ſhall lykewyſe do,</l>
                  <l>Yf God graunte you ſpace to lyue thereunto,</l>
                  <l>Suerly it appeareth quod I, ye haue a good memorye,</l>
                  <l>Whiche can the tyme of youre youthe declare ſo perfectlye,</l>
                  <l>And for this youre longe tale nowe I thancke you good father,</l>
                  <l>But for your loue Grace whoſe chaunce was to haue hir,</l>
                  <l>Marte quod he afterwarde within leſſe then a yere,</l>
                  <l>She toke a ſeruynge man agaynſte hir frendes wyll there,</l>
                  <l>Betwene whome was nothynge but chydynge and ſtryfe,</l>
                  <l>Brawlynge and fyghtynge all her longe lyſe,</l>
                  <l>And beggers bothe they became at the laſte,</l>
                  <l>She was an yll huſwyfe, and he ſpente as faſte,</l>
                  <l>So that they were compelled within yeres one or two,</l>
                  <l>Wanderynge a beggynge bothe for to goo,</l>
                  <l>Whiche greued me muche when theyr myſerie I knewe,</l>
                  <l>And then ſomewhat I relieued them for myne olde loue true,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>THIS haue I tolde thee (my ſonne) for this entente,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe thy follye hereafter thou myghteſt preuente,</l>
                  <l>And not to loue one before hir maners thou do knowe,</l>
                  <l>But fyrſte knowe hir, then loue hir, and ſo it wyll growe,</l>
                  <l>To berve good purpoſe, ende, and effecte,</l>
                  <l>And all other vayne haſtye lour ſe thou neglecte,</l>
                  <l>And when thou meaneſt a wyfe for to chuſe,</l>
                  <l>My counſayle in this cace ſe that thou vſe,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:20"/>
                  <l>Fyrſte hir mothers maners learne yf thou can,</l>
                  <l>And hir fathers alſo whether he be an honeſt man,</l>
                  <l>For commonly the chyldren them ſelues do enclyne,</l>
                  <l>To theyr parentes condicions as ſtrayght as a lyne,</l>
                  <l>Further enquyre of the neyghbours dwellynge there aboute,</l>
                  <l>Of what honeſtie ſhe is by the voyce of the route,</l>
                  <l>Or yf there be any honeſt woman dwellynge nere,</l>
                  <l>Sende hir cloſely thither, hir bothe to ſe and heare,</l>
                  <l>Whether ſhe be fayre, and of bodye cleane,</l>
                  <l>Or diſeaſyde or ſicklie by any maner of meane,</l>
                  <l>For (ſonne) no man wyl bye horſe, oxe, cowe, or calfe,</l>
                  <l>But he wyll fyrſte be full ſure they ſhalbe ſounde and ſafe,</l>
                  <l>Muche more circumſpecte a man ought to be in choice of his wyfs,</l>
                  <l>With whom he muſt liue all the dayes of hys lyfe,</l>
                  <l>Who yf ſhe be vncleane or infected with any kynde of dyſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>All thy children of nature ſhal haue the ſame ſickneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Alſo cauſe the ſame woman dilygentlye to knowe,</l>
                  <l>Yf ſhe be folyſhe neyther can ſpynne nor ſowe,</l>
                  <l>For in theſe thynges I ſaye eche woman that is chaſte,</l>
                  <l>Wyll exercyſe hir ſelfe, and no tyme ydellye waſte,</l>
                  <l>For ydelneſſe is the noryſher of vyces all,</l>
                  <l>And the ſame cauſeth the mynde in muche myſchiefe to fall,</l>
                  <l>This ydleneſſe many welthy fayre cities decayeth,</l>
                  <l>Fyſthye luſte, alſo ydelnes euer followeth,</l>
                  <l>Yf eyther chaſte Pennellope or fayre Lucreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Had ſpente their tyme ſyttinge at home in ydelneſſe,</l>
                  <l>And not geuen them ſelues to weuynge, and ſpynnynge,</l>
                  <l>In their huſbandes abſence from the begynnynge,</l>
                  <l>Of a thouſande woars whiche daylye to them came,</l>
                  <l>They ſhould ſuerly haue concented to ſome one man,</l>
                  <l>But touchynge the ſerche of hir lyfe and modeſtie,</l>
                  <l>Theſe thinges thy ſelfe maieſt muche better eſpye,</l>
                  <l>For all people nowe are waren ſo vniuſte,</l>
                  <l>That fewe ſhalt thou fynde whome thou maieſt truſte,</l>
                  <l>Yt is nowe the maner of many to deteaue and lye,</l>
                  <l>Fewe are there to be founde of credit worthye,</l>
                  <l>Therfore yf thou wylt haue thy purpoſe take effecte,</l>
                  <l>It be houeth the therein to be carefull and circumſpecte,</l>
                  <l>And ſonne, herein lyeth all youre marrynge and makynge,</l>
                  <l>Yf ye be not warelye wyſe in youre wyfe takynge,</l>
                  <l>Conſyderynge no ſmall tyme ye together ſhall remayne,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:21"/>
                  <l>But euen tyl death ſhal ſeperate the lyues of you twayne,</l>
                  <l>In all other caſes raſhenes, and haſt is but follye,</l>
                  <l>But in this matter may it bring intollerable myſerye,</l>
                  <l>Therfore this choice of thy wyfe fyrſte ponder wittelye,</l>
                  <l>That thou repent not hereafter when it is paſt al remedye,</l>
                  <l>But if it happen the as it dothe to many other moo,</l>
                  <l>That thy wyfe thou ſhalt mary perchaunce be a Shrewe,</l>
                  <l>Fyrſte gentlye warne hir, and with louynge ſpeche,</l>
                  <l>Do thy beſt hir to chaſten, and mildely hir teache,</l>
                  <l>And often hir fauour by fayre meanes to obtayne,</l>
                  <l>Enbrace hir wyth kyſſes to reconcyle hir agayne,</l>
                  <l>Thus by gentylneſſe yf thou can do thy beſt hir to tame,</l>
                  <l>Whiche yf it wyll not hir in nowyſe reclayme,</l>
                  <l>Then ſharper medecines thou muſt put in vre,</l>
                  <l>By threates, feare, and chidynge to bring hir to thy lure,</l>
                  <l>Whiche yf ſhe regarde not nor ſtande yet in awe,</l>
                  <l>The laſte helpe of all is that ſtrokes muſt then followe,</l>
                  <l>Nowe concernynge the conſeruacion of thy wyfes chaſtitye,</l>
                  <l>I wyll not muche ſpeake in that matter trulye,</l>
                  <l>But this may I ſaye, and I dare vndertake,</l>
                  <l>That oft a wyſe man an honeſt woman dothe make,</l>
                  <l>I coulde herein tell thee more, but I wyl not nowe,</l>
                  <l>For I leaue the ſame hollye to the diſcrecion of you,</l>
                  <l>Yet to learne this one leſſon, I would haue the (good ſonne,)</l>
                  <l>Neuer let thy fancie or deſyre after any other to ronne,</l>
                  <l>But in wedlocke be to hir as faithfull and true,</l>
                  <l>As the Turtel which neuer wil chafige hir make for a newe,</l>
                  <l>For there is no one thinge thy wyfe wyl take more greuouſlye,</l>
                  <l>Nor any other thynge vereth hir ſpirites ſo vehemently,</l>
                  <l>Nor of nothynge deſyreth ſhe ſo ſoone to be reuenged,</l>
                  <l>As in that one poynte if hir huſbande haue offended,</l>
                  <l>Then wareth ſhe hote incenſyd with yre,</l>
                  <l>With diſpyte and malyce then hir harte is on fyre,</l>
                  <l>In which their furiouſe rage ſome ſeke the waye than,</l>
                  <l>In lyke ſorte (if they may) to deceaue their good man,</l>
                  <l>Beleue me (ſonne) ſewe of them will kepe their honeſtie,</l>
                  <l>Yf their huſbandes in ſuche wyſe do lyue abrode viſiouſlye,</l>
                  <l>Further thy children hereafter ſee thou vp brynge,</l>
                  <l>In vertuouſe excercyſe and alſo good learnynge,</l>
                  <l>Teache theim to feare God and the to obaye,</l>
                  <l>And euer kepe them in obedience as muche as thou maye,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:21"/>
                  <l>For they wyll euer waxe bolde as nede ſhall requyre,</l>
                  <l>But not alwayes ſo humble as thou wouldeſt deſyre,</l>
                  <l>Therfore whyle they are younge and tender of yeres,</l>
                  <l>Is bothe their helpe, and vndoynge, as it oft apperes,</l>
                  <l>Muche paynes muſte thou take in godly inſtructynge theim,</l>
                  <l>Yf thou purpoſe they ſhal euer proue honeſt men,</l>
                  <l>Lauſe them al euel company to exchue continually,</l>
                  <l>For iuſte he cannot be that is conuerſaunte with the vngodly,</l>
                  <l>One ſhepe hauyngs a peryllouſe pocke,</l>
                  <l>Of force muſte enfecte all the hole flocke,</l>
                  <l>Thy daughters alwayes with ſhamefaſtnes vprere,</l>
                  <l>For it is the faireſt flower all women can were,</l>
                  <l>Let them neuer be ydle but alwayes doynge,</l>
                  <l>With the whele, the diſtafe, or with the nedle ſowynge,</l>
                  <l>For the welfare of this ſexe ſtandeth in their honeſtye,</l>
                  <l>Which when they are ydle, is then in moſt ieoperdye,</l>
                  <l>And at their ripe yeres do it not ouer ſlyde,</l>
                  <l>Some honeſt huſbandes for theim to prouyde,</l>
                  <l>Be not bitter (good ſonne) to thy ſeruauntes at any tyme,</l>
                  <l>Neither punyſhe theim with rigoure for euery cryme,</l>
                  <l>There is a meane to be obſerued in correccion I ſaye,</l>
                  <l>By whiche thou maieſt cauſe them thee both to loue &amp; obaye,</l>
                  <l>And althoughe fortune hathe poynted the their mayſter to be,</l>
                  <l>He myght lykewyſe haue made a ſeruaunte of the,</l>
                  <l>And what hereafter may fall no man knoweth his chaunce,</l>
                  <l>For the hole ſtate of mans lyfe dependeth in ballaunce,</l>
                  <l>I haue knowen dyuerſe men, bothe riche and welthye,</l>
                  <l>That afterwarde haue fallen in ſuche myſerye,</l>
                  <l>That full fayne they haue bene to auoyde vyle beggerye,</l>
                  <l>By ſeruyce to lyue in great callamitie,</l>
                  <l>What we are &amp; haue bene we knowe, but what after we ſhalbe,</l>
                  <l>We are ignoraunte therof ſuche is oure vncertayntye,</l>
                  <l>In thy fyrſte kepynge of hduſe be not to ſumptuouſe,</l>
                  <l>Neyther in foode nor apparell to laciuiouſe,</l>
                  <l>For at thy pleaſure thou mayeſt the ſame alway amende,</l>
                  <l>When God aboundaunce of ſubſtaunce hereafter ſhall ſende,</l>
                  <l>But it woulde be to thy ſhame, yf thou ſhouldeſt aſlake,</l>
                  <l>The fyrſte honneſt porte thou diddeſt vpon the take,</l>
                  <l>Often call home thy neyghbours, but moſt ſuche as are poore,</l>
                  <l>To dyne and ſuppe with the, let ſome of them be ſure,</l>
                  <l>The Lorde thy table ſhall bleſſe the more,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:22"/>
                  <l>And for ſuche liberallitie he wil encreaſe thy ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Go not to lawe with them, nor be no extoretoner,</l>
                  <l>Finyſhe their cauſes yf thou maieſt, and be no bearer,</l>
                  <l>In no mans mattier but in all that thou caune,</l>
                  <l>Set quietneſſe and concorde betwene man and man,</l>
                  <l>But in wranglinge matters be in no wyſe no medler,</l>
                  <l>Whiche myghte get the an yll name, and no man the better,</l>
                  <l>Further yf thou fynde a man of an approued honeſtye,</l>
                  <l>That feareth God, and is geuen to good vertues hollye,</l>
                  <l>Of whome moſte men ſayewell, for his good lyuynge,</l>
                  <l>That is no drunckarde, quarrelloure, nor delyteth in ſtriuig,</l>
                  <l>But quyet ſober, and learned in ſapience,</l>
                  <l>Beynge of good iudgemente, and alſo of good experience,</l>
                  <l>This mans frendſhyp ſeke buſelye to obtayne,</l>
                  <l>For then a faythe full frende there is no greater gayne,</l>
                  <l>But er thou hys amitie earniſtlie embrace,</l>
                  <l>Learne howe he hath vſed hys other frendes in lyke cate,</l>
                  <l>For ſuche as his behauioure hathe bene to other moe,</l>
                  <l>Truſte me (ſonne) he wylorder the euen ſo,</l>
                  <l>And when thou once haſte him thy frende vnfeynedly,</l>
                  <l>Then ſeke to continue in frendſhyp dillygentlye,</l>
                  <l>Let no lyght, dyſpleaſure, the ſame breake or decaye,</l>
                  <l>But beare with hym rather in all that thou maye,</l>
                  <l>Of all treaſure the chefeſt that God dothe in earthe ſende,</l>
                  <l>Is a man to haue alwayes a ſure and ſtedfaſt frende,</l>
                  <l>Furthermore yf ſyckneſſe ſhall vere the or thyne,</l>
                  <l>Se thou miniſter remedye to the ſame betyme,</l>
                  <l>Or euer the ſame do augment and encreaſe,</l>
                  <l>The ſoner ſhal it mende, and the grefe be the leſſe,</l>
                  <l>For lyke as fyre when it is fyrſte begonne,</l>
                  <l>With a lyttel water wylbe quenched full ſoone,</l>
                  <l>But yf it be ſuffered to contynue ſtylle,</l>
                  <l>And a whyle to burne euen at his owne wyll,</l>
                  <l>Then the flame wylbe rayſed in ſuche a great rage,</l>
                  <l>That hole welles and conduictes can ſcace it aſwage,</l>
                  <l>Euen ſo euery malladye at the fyrſte entraunce,</l>
                  <l>Maye be eaſely cured without great greuaunce,</l>
                  <l>This fyrſte poynt of phiſycke learne thou of me,</l>
                  <l>Yf the ſycknes be hote, colde, or moyſte, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remedy muſt be contrarye,</l>
                  <l>If ouer much laboure, and trauayle be the cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Then by eaſe, and reſt from the ſame, thou muſt pauſe,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:22"/>
                  <l>And yf the ſame come by ouer muche eaſe and reſt,</l>
                  <l>Then exercyſe and moderate laboure is beſt,</l>
                  <l>Yf it be by ſuperfluitye of drincke or meate,</l>
                  <l>Then abſtmence is the beſt remedie thou can get,</l>
                  <l>And yf nede requyre a phiſicion then call,</l>
                  <l>Or a ſurgion, but good diet is the beſt lieche of all,</l>
                  <l>The ſurgion is nerte, for phiſicions do kyll,</l>
                  <l>The moſte part that put their truſte theim vntyll,</l>
                  <l>For where by happe ſome one they do ſaue,</l>
                  <l>A hundred for hym they ſende to theyr graue,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>ALSO my ſonne this laſte precepte thou muſte learne,</l>
                  <l>Which dilygently to obſerue I the earniſtlye warne,</l>
                  <l>Be prepared alwayes, and euermore full redye,</l>
                  <l>Deathe to enbrace where he ſtriketh ſoudenlye,</l>
                  <l>Yea euen in his mooſt Luſt and welthieſt tyme,</l>
                  <l>Let the remembraunce of hym be ſtyll before thyne yene,</l>
                  <l>He aſſaulteth men comonly when they thinke of hym leſt,</l>
                  <l>Fearcelye inuadynge them in their moſte quietnes and reſt,</l>
                  <l>He draweth euer nexer with his ineuitable darte,</l>
                  <l>Daylye percynge euery age of man to the harte,</l>
                  <l>Howe often dothe death ſtrike the younge luſtye man,</l>
                  <l>And beryeueth hym of hys beſt yeres we ſe nowe and than,</l>
                  <l>Oh howe great are the trauayles and payne,</l>
                  <l>That a man in this lyfe with payne dothe ſuſtayne,</l>
                  <l>Howe ſhorte is our tyme and the ſame alſo ſo varyable,</l>
                  <l>That nothynge in this lyfe can be founde ſtable,</l>
                  <l>With what innumerable pylles are we beſeged,</l>
                  <l>Whiche by this oure frayle nature can neuer be reſyted,</l>
                  <l>What we oure vayne pleaſures wherin we ſo truſte,</l>
                  <l>Euen poyſoned with galle and cankered with ruſte,</l>
                  <l>What are we owretches but duſte of the ayre,</l>
                  <l>As bryttell as glaſſe ſeme it neuer ſo fayre,</l>
                  <l>Moſte lyke to a ſhadowe in a ſonnye daye,</l>
                  <l>Which when the cloudes are aloſt ſodenly vanyſhe a waye,</l>
                  <l>Lyke as a flower whiche floriſheth in the mornynge dew,</l>
                  <l>And at nyghte is withered and hathe vaded his hewe,</l>
                  <l>For thoughe we are now alyue, and luſtye in euery mans ſight,</l>
                  <l>Fayre, amiable, pleaſaunte, full of corage and might,</l>
                  <l>Yet perchaunce er Ppheabus hath once his courſe ronne,</l>
                  <l>Deade carcaſſes we may be and vyle meate for the worme,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:23"/>
                  <l>What proſyteth vs then our great ſommes of monye,</l>
                  <l>Heaped together by extorcion and bryberye,</l>
                  <l>Golde, ſtones, Iewels, or implement moſt preciouſe,</l>
                  <l>Landes, houſes, or vyllages, be they neuer ſo ſumptuous,</l>
                  <l>Eyther worſhip honour, or lordely auctoritie,</l>
                  <l>Rule or dominion or worldely dignitie,</l>
                  <l>Whiche maketh many men ſo proudely to looke ouer all,</l>
                  <l>As thoughe they were to the goddes coequall,</l>
                  <l>Seinge death endeth althynge, and we wretches wyth myſery,</l>
                  <l>Lyke duſte and ſhadowe conſume ſo ſodenly,</l>
                  <l>Semge all oure pryde and glory is ſo ſone extinguyſhed,</l>
                  <l>And oure tyme ſo quickly gone neuer to be recouered.</l>
                  <l>O lyfe ſo vayne ſo fugitiue and frayle,</l>
                  <l>Whome ſuche a nomber of daungers and perſilles do aſſaſlle.</l>
                  <l>O lyfe that arte ſo ſhorte, and vncertayne,</l>
                  <l>Moſt lyke vnto ſmoke, a man can the licken,</l>
                  <l>Nowe this man dyeth an other after hym,</l>
                  <l>I to daye perchaunce, and thou to morowe betyme,</l>
                  <l>So a lyttel, and a lytle, eche man dothe dye,</l>
                  <l>Euen lyke a butcher hauynge ſhepe and beſtes many,</l>
                  <l>Of whiche ſome to daye he kylleth downe ryght,</l>
                  <l>And other ſome to morow in the morning, or at nyght,</l>
                  <l>The nerte daye other moo go to the blocke,</l>
                  <l>And ſo forthe tyll conſumed be all the hole flocke,</l>
                  <l>Thus death dayly remember but feare not the ſame,</l>
                  <l>For of it ſelfe it is good and worthye no blame,</l>
                  <l>Deathe fynyſheth all paynes, death endeth all care,</l>
                  <l>Death daungers diſſolueth, and putteth away feare,</l>
                  <l>To the poore, to the priſonner, and to the comfortleſſe,</l>
                  <l>To the condemned, and to the miſerable captyue in diſſreſſe,</l>
                  <l>To the bondeman, ſlaue, ſpoyled, and Lazar impotente,</l>
                  <l>To them that are on the racke, and in greuouſe tormente,</l>
                  <l>Deathe is imbraced and hartely welcome,</l>
                  <l>To ſuche and many other of lyke ſtate and condicion,</l>
                  <l>To good men, death neuer can come vnware,</l>
                  <l>Whiche euer againſt his commynge them ſelues do prepare.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe lyfe hathe contynued in ryghteouſneſſe,</l>
                  <l>And whyche haue remayned in faythe, mercy, and godlyneſſe,</l>
                  <l>To them no dyſproffit is deathe but aduauntage,</l>
                  <l>Althoughe it take them in theyr mooſte flouryſhynge age,</l>
                  <l>Thus yf thou be good receaue deathe gladlye,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:23"/>
                  <l>For it is a paſſynge oute of this vale of myſerye,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhalte thou render to the earthe and againe to hir ſende,</l>
                  <l>Thy body whiche but for a tyme ſhe did vnto the lende,</l>
                  <l>And if thou ponder with thy ſelfe in thy minde diſcretlye,</l>
                  <l>What dammage or hurte can death do vnto the,</l>
                  <l>She ſpoilleth the of thy riches perchaunce thou wylt ſaye,</l>
                  <l>But then riches wanteſt thou none by no kynde of waie,</l>
                  <l>Nor anie other thing els thy ſoule ſhall deſyre,</l>
                  <l>But from pouertie to riches thou then ſemeſt to aſpire,</l>
                  <l>For he of all other is the richeſte in dede,</l>
                  <l>Nor that hathe mooſte but that feweſt thinges doth nede,</l>
                  <l>To leaue thy wyſe, childerne &amp; frendes, is a miſerable thinge,</l>
                  <l>Yea, but it wer much more miſerable to ſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> die the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liuinge,</l>
                  <l>And it wyll not be longe but they ſhall folowe the,</l>
                  <l>When the lorde ſhall alſo call for them accordinglye,</l>
                  <l>And theſe worldly riches and pleaſures are none of thine,</l>
                  <l>But lent to the as it weare for a litle tyme,</l>
                  <l>Naked cameſt thou hether and naked muſt thou hence go,</l>
                  <l>Therfore for terreſtriall trifles ſorowe not ſo,</l>
                  <l>This world is as it were a certaine great feaſte,</l>
                  <l>Where vnto euery man is bidden as a geaſte,</l>
                  <l>Where for a while duringe the Lordes pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>We haue the fruition of this vayne worldlye treaſure,</l>
                  <l>Vpon this condicion that we be alwayes ready,</l>
                  <l>At his commaundement to giue place and departe gladlye,</l>
                  <l>And to ſuffer other men that after vs ſhall come,</l>
                  <l>Of the ſame feaſt to receaue like fruition,</l>
                  <l>What wight wyl not willinglye leaue this lotheſome lyfe,</l>
                  <l>Whiche is ſo wicked diſceatfull and ſo full of ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>Where no fayth, no pietie, nor any iuſtice,</l>
                  <l>Remaineth neither any quietnes or peace,</l>
                  <l>Wher all kinde of Sinnes euermore do raigne,</l>
                  <l>Where the brother is comonly the brothers bayne,</l>
                  <l>Where the ſonne ofte wiſheth for his fathers ſhorte lyfe,</l>
                  <l>The woman hir huſbande, and the huſbande his wife,</l>
                  <l>Whereche body catheth &amp; ſnatcheth what he can,</l>
                  <l>Beinge diſſemblers and wourkers of fraude euery man,</l>
                  <l>That this worlde maie wourthelye well be named,</l>
                  <l>A denne of theues being with pillinge and polling enflamed,</l>
                  <l>Of luſte and boredome what ſhould I make mencion,</l>
                  <l>Wherwith the hole earth is fylled with like abhominacion,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22727:24"/>
                  <l>That chaſtifie is banyſhed and virgynitie defaced,</l>
                  <l>And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honorable ſacreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Matrimonie nothing regarded</l>
                  <l>In which wicked worlde alſo are of parels ſo many,</l>
                  <l>Of labors and ſicknes ſuche a nombre and ſondery,</l>
                  <l>Where fortune onelye ruleth without all reaſon,</l>
                  <l>Wher no man of him ſelf can be aſſured any ſeaſon,</l>
                  <l>What good man will not nowe leaue this world gladly,</l>
                  <l>Whiche is hollye compaſſed with ſuch vntollerable myſery,</l>
                  <l>Wherefore great follye it is death for to feare,</l>
                  <l>Seinge it endeth the myſeries we ſuſtayne here,</l>
                  <l>And conſyder alſo that departynge from mortallitie,</l>
                  <l>By death thou entereſt into thy region of eternitie,</l>
                  <l>Therfore my ſonne let thy lyfe be godlye,</l>
                  <l>So ſhalte thou not ſtande in any feare to dye,</l>
                  <l>Fyrſte in thy health, hollye ſet in good ſtaye,</l>
                  <l>By wyll, al thy worldly affaires as nere as thou maye,</l>
                  <l>That in thy ſicknes thou be not with them troubled,</l>
                  <l>Nor thy mynde then from godlyneſſe by them encombred,</l>
                  <l>And euery nyghte before thou goeſt to thy reſt,</l>
                  <l>To confeſſe to God thy ſynnes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> harty repentaunce is beſt,</l>
                  <l>And humblye aſke mercy with hope vnſaynedly,</l>
                  <l>Preparynge thy ſelfe then holly to dye,</l>
                  <l>And ſo thy ſoule to the Lorde mooſt humblye betake,</l>
                  <l>Which on the croſſe ſuffred his paſſion for thy ſake,</l>
                  <l>Thus ſhal not ſoden death vnprouyded the fynde,</l>
                  <l>Yf thou beare well this laſt leſſon in thy mynde,</l>
                  <l>This my rude counſayle yf thou followe in euery condicion,</l>
                  <l>As I truſt thou wylt accordynge to myne expectacion,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt well walke in the right pathe waye than,</l>
                  <l>Whiche as I erſte ſayde leadeth to the lyfe of an honeſt man,</l>
                  <l>And now ſonne my former promyſe beynge performed &amp; done,</l>
                  <l>To the place where we met we are nere efteſones come,</l>
                  <l>I thancke you gentle father ſayd I for your holſome counſayle,</l>
                  <l>I neuer herde tolde a more verteouſe tale,</l>
                  <l>I beſeche almyghty God to graunte me the grace,</l>
                  <l>The ſame to obſerue in euery poynte and cace,</l>
                  <l>And the ſame Lorde of hys goodnes rewarde you gratiouſlye,</l>
                  <l>That hathe taken ſuche paynes to enſtructe me verteouſlye,</l>
                  <l>Fare well my good ſonne quod he Chriſt be thy guyde,</l>
                  <l>And ſo departynge from hym home warde I hyed,</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:22727:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
